Bryce shrinking every minute...
Bryce shrinking every minute...
Karamati because I needed...
Karamati because I needed...
life...
life...
to jump over gate and man....
to jump over gate and man....
now Siro appears out of nowhere.
now Siro appears out of nowhere.
He has two brothers and favorite….
He has two brothers and favorite….
so he is named 6...
so he is named 6...
Siro appear in this movie.
Siro appear in this movie.
He has 4 brothers and 1 sister.
He has 4 brothers and 1 sister.
He always been before hisoscope.
He always been before hisoscope.
Here is a version.
Here is a version.
Lemmemayın siro S this thing
Lemmemayın siro S 這個東西
you have to get by ASAP.
you have to get by ASAP.
Can much beat Master Ching Somebody's現在...
Can much beat Master Ching Somebody's現在...
Thank you.
Thank you.
Yang Cuisheng, the former county magistrate of our Matsu County
我們馬祖縣的前縣長楊崔昇縣長
mazu county magistrate
馬祖縣長
Members
各位會員
today we have a
今天我們有一個
please sit down
先請坐
The topic is
要講題目是
Archaeological excavations on Xianya
賢崖上的考古發掘
Talking about the Unearthed Story of the Old Man Liang
漫談量老人出土的故事
I want to measure what the old man unearthed
我想量老人出土的事情
among the newspapers
在報紙之中
in learning
在學習之內
reports with a lot of information
有很多資料的報導
So these important archaeological excavations
那麼這些重要的考古發掘
Everyone must notice
各位一定注意到
our knowledge misses
我們的知識想念
Because every year the humanities and social sciences
因為每年人文跟社科
only four times
也只有四次
so it's a great honor
所以也是一個很大的榮譽
great honor
很大的榮譽
Then our Mr. Chen
那我們陳先生
Actually retired from Academia Sinica
事實上已經從中研院退休
But his previous research
但是他之前的研究
then schedule this talk
那麼安排這個演講
there is an important reason
有一個重要原因
It is the beginning of the data equivalent to the elderly
就是當量老人的資料開始
at the time of publication
在公布的時候
Academician Xu Zhuoen of Academia Sinica
中研院的許卓恩院士
He Yueren is in the United States
他越人在美國
Ancient archaeology, paleontology, DNA, etc. are very, very concerned
古代考古啊古生物學這個這個DNA等等非常非常關注
So he wrote me that email several times specifically
所以呢他特地給我寫過幾次那個電郵
He said you as the vice president
他說你作為副院長
he this is a major and important discovery
他這是一個重大的一個重要的發現
He should try to give Mr. Chen an award
他應該要設法給陳先生頒一個獎項
I said I don't have a prize
我說我手上一個獎都沒有
So so I don't have an award to give to Mr. Chen
那麼所以我沒有獎可以頒給陳先生
Especially the humanities and social science awards are very, very few
尤其人文社科學獎非常少非常少
Then some prizes may be too small for Mr. Chen
那麼有一些獎可能對陳先生已經太小了
Well at least I don't have it I don't have it
那麼至少我沒有我手上沒有
I said I thought about it and couldn't think of a way
我說我想了想去想不出一個辦法
Later, I thought that the feast of knowledge is actually an occasion for affirming important achievements
後來我想到知識饗宴其實等於也是一個肯定重要成績的一個場合
So there is such an arrangement
所以有這樣一個安排
Because Mr. Chen has usually knowledge feast if yours is usually not retired
因為陳先生已經通常知識饗宴如果願你的通常都是沒有退休的
Well, those outside the hospital are of course still working.
那麼院外的當然都是也都還是正在工作崗位上
Because I have been retired for many years
因為已經退休多年
So today we are looking for this opportunity
那麼今天我們特地找這個機會
There is a reason for arranging this speech
來安排這個演講是有這樣一層原因的
Well, I think this is the first thing to explain
那麼我覺得這個是要首先說明
It is Xu Zhuoenyuan because he has ancient history before
就是許卓恩院是因為他之前就上古史
He has been concerned about this ancient archaeological
他一直對這個古代的這個相關的考古
very concerned
非常關注
he this
他這個
I want to keep this around 2011
這個我想要保留在2011年前後呢
What about the Mazu Liang Island archaeological team led by Mr. Chen?
由這個陳先生率領的馬祖亮島考古隊呢
Execute excavation work
執行發掘的工作
Well, two human remains were unearthed.
那麼出土了兩具人類遺骸
Named Bright Island Man
命名為亮島人
After the human bones have been cleaned and trimmed
經過人骨經過清理修整之後
Delivery to Max Planck, Germany
送到德國Max Planck
the Max Blanc Institute
就是馬克思布朗克研究所
To do this DNA extraction analysis
去做這個DNA的這個萃取分析
very good results
取得了成果非常之好
Because Taiwan is a wet
因為台灣是一個潮濕這個
hot and humid place
熱又潮濕的地方
So many of our ancient bones
所以我們很多古代的骨頭
Difficult to extract DNA
很難萃取DNA
so this
所以這
This is surprisingly good
這個呢 意外的好
as far as i know
就我個人所知
i am not an archaeologist
我不是考古學家
but as far as i know
但就我個人所知
unexpectedly good
意外的好
So this is a very difficult achievement
所以這是一個很不容易的一個成果
Then after the comparison
那麼比對了之後呢
got a result that is
得到了一個結果就是
Quantitative guides are 8000 years away from today
量導人在距離今天8000年
Or earlier, the southeastern part of the Asian continent
或更早的亞洲大陸東南一帶
aborigines
存在著有跟台灣原住民
people of the same blood
相同血緣的人種
Can be called the original Nandao Yuzu
可以稱為原南島羽族
They most likely came from the southeast coast of mainland China
他們極可能是從中國大陸東南沿海
thus come
因而而來
Therefore, the formation of the Nandaoyu tribe
因而南島羽族的生成
can be pushed back nearly 8,000 years
可以向前推到近8000年前
This is because quite specialized
這個是因為相當專門
I can't quite grasp it either
我也不是完全能把握
I am the Yu family from about 8000 years ago
我就是大概是8000年前的這個羽族
8000 years ago this
8000年前的這個
Then the other is today's keynote speaker
那麼另外就是今天的主講者
What about Professor Chen Zhongyi?
陳忠義教授呢
is my colleague for 30 years
是我30年的同事
Actually, I just entered Academia Sinica
其實我剛進中研院
Has been in Academia Sinica for 30 years
已經進中研院30年
So
那麼
when i first came in
我剛進來的時候
when a child comes in
一個小孩子進來的時候
At that time, Mr. Chen was already
那時候陳先生就已經是
Madam save life
夫人救人台生
Mr Chen is a
陳先生是一個
An example of successful self-study
自學苦學成功的一個例子
he in 1955
他在1955年
Entered Academia Sinica after graduating from high school
高中畢業就進到中研院了
so he is very few
所以他是很少數
Among the colleagues we are familiar with now
我們現在熟悉的這個同事裡面
Worked with Dean Hu
跟胡事院長一起工作過的
so used to
所以慣
Mr. Chen also told me
陳先生還告訴我過
Dean Hu follows this
胡事院長跟在這個
meeting of academicians
院士的會議上
There are many inside stories about conflicts with President Chiang
這個很多跟蔣總統衝突的內幕
he was there
他也在場
So he is a very senior colleague
所以呢他是非常前輩的這個同事
He later worked in the Department of History
他後來在施大歷史系
After graduating from the National Taiwan University Institute of Archeology
在台大考古研究所畢業之後
So officially become a researcher
所以就正式成為研究人員
but it is important that he
但是很重要的是他
He is the assistant of Mr. Li Ji, the chief teacher of the third group of archeology
他是考古學開三組主師李季先生的助手
So he, a senior in archaeology who came into contact with
所以他這個所接觸到的考古學的前輩
Much
非常多
Then after the 1980s
後來在1980年代以後呢
He changed from Taiwan
他改從台灣
and marine island archeology
和海洋島嶼考古學
In Taipei County, Nantou County, Pingdong County, Hualien County, Taitung County, Kinmen County, Lianjiang County
在台北縣市南投縣平東縣花蓮縣台東縣金門縣連江縣
has his important archaeological discoveries
都有他重要的考古發現
Everyone, if you go to Puri, there is a site called Qubing
各位如果去普里有一個叫做取兵遺址
I remember that this site also presents this
我記得這個取兵遺址也是呈現這個
The Bibing Site in Puri is now also a place to visit
取兵遺址普里的取兵遺址現在也是一個遊覽參觀的地方
So next time you go, you can pay a little attention
所以下次各位去可以稍微注意一下
But more importantly, he discovered this 8,000-year-old historical record in Matsu three years ago.
但是更重要的是三年前他在馬祖發現了這個八千年前的史稱
Liangdao Ruins in the New Era
新時期時代的量島遺址
with two islanders
跟兩具量島人
present this daily research
呈現這個日常研究
More professional research and less teaching in China
專業研究比較多很少在國內教書
But he was also in Thailand
不過他也曾經在泰國的
Xi Jinping University and Xiamen University have been visiting professors
是習近平大學還有廈門大學做過訪問教授
He is also a member of the Art Center for Chinese Archaeological Research at the Chinese University of Hong Kong.
他同時也在香港中文大學中文考古研究藝術中心
Honorary Research Fellow, Jianqiao University and University of California, Random Seven
名譽研究員、建橋大學跟加州大學亂七分校
And visiting scholars at the University of Arizona, the Department of Anthropology, etc.
以及亞利桑那大學、人類學系等地的訪問學人
I think his efforts are very admirable
我覺得他的努力非常的令人敬佩
especially after he retires
尤其他在退休之後退而不休
There is another important discovery that I find very rare
還有一個重要的發現我覺得非常難得
So now we welcome him with a round of applause
那麼現在我們就以熱烈掌聲歡迎他
associate dean
副院長
The incumbent Yang county magistrate
在位的楊縣長
Many colleagues in our institute
許多我們研究院的同仁
advanced
先進
many my neighbors
許多我的鄰居
my friend
我的朋友
And many friends outside our hospital
還有我們院外的很多朋友
what a great honor today
今天真是非常榮幸
I have the opportunity to report my recent work to the chairman
我有的機會能夠向主委報告我最近的工作
It has been fourteen years since Chen Rou Fuyuan talked about the special break
陳柔復元長講的特休已經十四年了
i have to do it again
我還要再做 再工作
So here are four opportunities
所以這是 四個機遇
I'm thinking
我在想
This is the Central Research Institute
這個 作為中央研究院
I went from technician to researcher
我從技術人員到研究人員
Well actually like
那麼 其實像
knowledge miss this
知識想念這個
This presentation is actually a dream of our researchers.
這個演講其實是我們研究人員的一個夢想
because we know
因為我們知道
There are only four liberal arts students a year
文科一年只有四位
There are thousands of people in our research institute
我們研究院好幾千人
so i have a chance
所以我有的機會
Is to become the deputy dean's outsider
就是成這個副院長的台外
schedule this presentation
安排這一次的演講
and all that I'm going to talk about today
還有我今天要講的所有的
story
故事
nonstop story
無斷故事
this story
這故事
this is good
這個是好
There are so many links that link each other
有多的環節 節節相扣
Missing a link Our success rate
缺一個環節 我們的成功率
will not have a good success rate
就不會有很好的成功率
this so slowly let me come
這個 所以慢慢的讓我到來
i think we forgot one thing
我想 我們忘了一件事
i just forgot one thing
我只忘了一件事
I have a gift for Yang Xianchang
我這個有一件禮物送給楊憲長
This gift can currently be opened without first opening
這個禮物目前可以不必先打開
because wait a minute there will be
因為等一下炮炮會有
show something
顯出來什麼東西
Am I the vice president now, please?
我現在是不是副院長麻煩你
Did I give it to him myself?
是不是 我自己送給他
That's calligraphy on clothes
那是衣服的書法
but you have one of my poems
但是你們有我的一句詩
wait a minute i will introduce
等一下我會介紹
Our topic for this story today is
這個故事我們今天的題目是
Archaeological treasures of Cliff Mountain
懸崖山的考古花絕
The story of the 8,000-year-old Ryoshima people
八千歲的兩島人的故事
I divide five stories
我分五個故事
Let's look at the following
我們先看下面
First of all, what I want to introduce is to ask
首先我要介紹的就是到底請問
Any ladies and gentlemen who have been to Matsu raise your hands please
有哪些先生女士去過馬祖的起舉手好不好
Wow so much
哇好多
I watched half of it
看一半了
very good very good thank you thank you
很好很好謝謝謝謝
This Mazu is really the one that Dean Fu mentioned just now.
這馬祖啊真是一個剛才傅院長在提啊
It's a beautiful scenery
真是風景美得不得了
does not belong to greek love sea does not belong to mediterranean
不屬於希臘愛情海不屬於地中海
So where are the two islands?
所以那麼兩島在什麼位置呢
It is the location between Beigang and Dongying, which is 27 kilometers away.
就是北岡跟東穎中間它隔距離27公里的這個位置
I'll talk about its importance in a moment
我等一下要講它的重要性
let's see the next one
我們看下一張
So this is the two islands
那麼這個就是兩島
to some seaside many in Matsu
到一些海边 马祖岛的许多
This island is all of this flower dry rock structure
这岛都是这种花干岩的结构
let's look at these
我们看一下这些
look again
再看一下
we can see this
这个我们可以看
That view is all mainland fishing boats
那个观点都是大陆的渔船
That's the mainland
那边就是大陆
Looking west from here is the mainland
这边西看就是大陆
let's take a look
一边我们看一下
Its shellfish are of course island shellfish
它的植贝当然是岛屿的植贝
Mostly herbaceous
大部分都是草本植物比较多
few woody plants
木本植物很少
But there are also paper vines that are good plants
但是也有纸藤是很好的植物
let's take a look
我们看一下
This is also a characteristic of Mazu
这个也是马祖的一个特点
migratory bird of its seabird season
它的海鸟季节的候鸟
When they arrive they have apotheosis
到的时候它们有神化治疗
Empty end fit
空嘴端配合
this tern
這一頭燕鷗
we look good
我們看相子
that's what tern means
這是燕鷗的意思
Mainland fishing boats often fish there
大陸的漁船經常在那裏捕魚
we look good
我們看相子
This is the first story
這是第一段故事的
how to tell the first story
第一段故事要怎麼講呢
the first story says
第一段故事說
The Liangdao archaeological site is reserved for those who are destined
量島考古遺址留待有緣人
how do you say this
這怎麼說
Let's go back to the map just now
我們再回到剛才那一個地圖
that map
那地圖
That map just now
剛才那一張地圖
right
對
The location of Liangdao is because it is between Beigang and Dongying
量島的位置因為在北岡跟東穎中間
When our two sides are facing each other
在我們兩岸對峙的時候
its positional importance
它的位置重要性
If this island is not guarded by our national army
假如這個島不是我們國軍在守的話
This cold line will be cut
這一條寒線是會被切斷的
will be cut off
會被切斷的
let's see and go back
我們再看再回到
when is this island
这个岛什么时候啊
It was the first time that the national army boarded to occupy this island
国军第一次登上去占领这个岛呢
Because it was an uninhabited island
因为原来是个无人岛
In fact, this island is no stranger to the Matsu people.
其实这岛对马祖人是不陌生的
Mount Heng in ancient times
古称恒山
it is no stranger
它是不陌生的
Also like the fishermen of Daegu Island in Kitaoka
也像北冈的大丘岛的渔民
Now many fishermen are talking
现在很多渔民都在讲
The fisheries there are very rich
那边渔厂非常丰富
go fishing there
都到那边去捕鱼
very strange
很好的陌生
But because of its importance when cross-strait confrontation
但是它因为在两岸对峙的时候的重要性
so then what
所以后来呢
When was this called and changed it to Langdao
这个什么时候称把它改成浪岛
The waves of the waves we don't know
海浪的浪我们不知道
no way
没有没办法可好
That's July 15, 1951
那就是1951年7月15号的时候
At that time the national army
那时候国军
We now call it the National Army
我们现在我称它国军
It's actually called the National Salvation Army
其实叫做恍共救国军
That is a force army of Emperor Fan
那个是帝藩的一个势力军
He has a Captain Li Chengshang
他有一位李承商這個隊長
led six landowners
帶領了六位地主
Seven people went up to plant the flag
七個人上去插旗
After that we will occupy the island
那以後我們就佔領這個島
But at that time, because of the supply, the island
但是那時候因為補給什麼這個島
very difficult
非常困難
It is very difficult to replenish Lulu Deficiency
路路虛虛補給非常困難
so sometimes there is occupation
所以有時候有佔領
sometimes there is no way
有時候就沒辦法
just wait
就空待人命
until 1965
一直到了1965年的時候
It was confirmed that a group of troops went up
才證實一批軍隊上去
But in 1966
但1966年的時候
At that time Chiang Ching-kuo
那個時候蔣經國
when he was the secretary of homeland security
那時候他是國安部長的時候
he changed the name
他改這個名字
He thinks it is the island standing in the sky that shines on the mainland
他認為是島立天中亮照大陸
So change to Liangdao
所以改成亮島
The name was changed at that time
這個名詞是那時候才改的
Then in 2011
那麼到2011年的時候
At that time there was a commemorative meeting on the island
那時候有一個紀念會登島
60th anniversary commemoration
六十周年一個紀念會
I'll tell his story later
我等一下再講他的故事
Let's see the next one
下面我們看下一張
at this time
這個時候
because of this commemoration
因為這個紀念會
You just invited Li Chengshang for this cup
你這個杯就請了把李承商
The original team members are now among the seven
原來的隊員現在七個人裡頭
Now there are only two left
現在只剩好像只剩兩位
He was invited to attend this meeting
他都請了上去去參加這個會
Go and see what the island is like now
去看看現在島的狀況
when
的時候
County Magistrate Yang invited by him
他邀請的楊縣長
County Magistrate Yang also went up
楊縣長也上去
also when going up
也上去的時候
County Magistrate Yang is a county magistrate with very good humanistic qualities
楊縣長是一個人文素養非常好的一位縣長
He has been on this island for sixty years
他這個島六十年來
In fact, in 1965, when a large number of our troops went up
其實在1965年我們大批軍隊上去的時候
In fact he drove that way and said
事實上他就開那個路來說
In fact it's hard
事實上就硬開了
open that road
那一条路一开
That chair should have sections cut out
那个椅子应该有断面要切出来的
should have appeared then
应该那时候就应该出现的
But until 60 years later
但是一直到了60年以后
Our county magistrate Yang went up to see
我们杨县长上去看
Oops, this is a back seed
哎呀这是背种
just notify me to investigate
就通知我去做调查
That's why I found this chair
于是才发现这个椅子
Let's look at the next one
我们再看下面一张
Then the shape of the guide is like this
那这导的形状就是这样子
That little red dot in the north
在北边的那一点红点
near the first position
就是第一个位置的附近
first position
第一个位置
The port that County Magistrate Yang went to is called Baisheng Port
杨县长上去的这个港叫做百圣港
Baishenggang, the back breed he looked at when he went up
百圣港他上去的时候看的那个背种
that's the place
那个就是那个地点
Later we saw that it was a chair from the Ming and Qing Dynasties
那个后来我们看是明清时代的椅子
that hand
那那手
let's see the next one
我们看下一张
this is history
这个就是历史
we don't know
我们不曉得
friend of this guide
这个量导的朋友
say
称
Mr. Chen Yiyong gave it to me
陳奕永先生他送我的
then it will be difficult
那時候將難倒
March 1965
1965年3月
Only when we officially have a large force can we go up
這時候我們正式有大的部隊才上去
Just put this army in the emperor
才把這個軍隊駐皇
Formal and discreet emperor
正式很慎重的駐皇
That's when I took the second picture
就是那個時候帶第二張來看
Pay attention to see that the equipment of their troops cannot be compared with today's
注意看他們這個部隊裝備跟今天不能比
it was very very hard
那時候是非常非常艱苦
I am in this six years
我在這個六年年代
when i was in the army
我當兵的時候
It was very hard back then
那時候真是非常艱苦的
ok let's see the next one
好我們再看下一張
This is after going up from Baishenggang
這個就是從白盛港上去以後
This place has a Xiaoliang Pavilion
這個有一個小樑亭的地方
That is the Ming and Qing Dynasties
那上面就是明清時代
In the back that County Magistrate Yang saw
楊縣長看到的背中
let's see the next one
我們看下一張
This is the first time I've been
這是我第一次被
When I climbed up, I was talking about the fact that there are
登上去的時候在說說其實旁邊都有
Both have this back phenomenon and back phenomenon
都有這個背的現象和背現象
let's see the next one
我們再看下一張
i have a poe
我有一個poe
This is the back
這個就是這些背
Actually this back
其實這個背
But because there are several floors piled up on the road
但是因為開著路堆幾層
not the original
不是原來的
let's see the next one
我們再看下一張
When we first went to investigate
我們第一次去調查的時候
we see this
我們看到這個
This is driving the road
這個開馬路開馬
it cuts the section
它切斷了這個斷面
so i see this
所以這個我一看
After this back becomes 50 centimeters
這背成50公分後
30 meters long
30米長了
all terrible
都不得了
I later I will
我後來我就
Let's go inside it first
我們就先去看它裡頭
because we all know
因為我們大家所知道
so-called back seeding
所謂的背種
Ashes may occur because the back becomes
因為背成可能發生灰
natural disaster
天然這個災害
natural
天然的
those climates what death
那些氣候什麼死亡
may occur
可能會發生被誠
That can't be called being planted
那個不能叫成被種
so-called archaeological species
所謂考古學的被種
It must be human food waste
一定裡面是人吃的廚餘
throw the husk there
把被殼丟的那裡
Because there are people in the abdomen
那裡頭因為有腹帶有人的
Many of our cultural relics are thrown inside
很多我們的文化遺物丟裡面
The broken nets that escaped everywhere were thrown away in there
逃遍破的破網破遍都丟了那裡面
That's why we call it seeded
所以我們才稱被種
we're together we're a team
我們就一起我們一個團隊
four of us go up
我們四個人上去
Let's just say I looked at that pottery
我們就說我一看那個陶片
i was startled
我嚇得一跳
Even the sons of Taiwan left without him
台灣子都沒有他走
looks like
看樣子
so let's see the next one
所以我們再看下一張
The most important thing is that when I investigate
最重要的就是我在調查的時候
The most important thing is this one of us
最重要的就是我們這一位
Now he is the curator of the Matsu Folklore Cultural and Military Museum
現在是馬祖民俗文武館館長
Mr. Pan Jianguo
潘建國先生
let's see the next one
我們再看下一張
Where is he
他在那裡
As soon as I say we are
我一說說我們在
bottom layer
最底層啊
We all dig a little bit of this back
我們都挖一點這個背
Cut the peach slices if you can
桃片能剪就剪一點
go back and make specimens
回去做標本
let's check
我們去檢查
For example, when he digs the back
比如說他就挖這個背的時候
He dug up the two sides
他就挖到了這兩邊東西
Three pieces in total
三片總共三片
He showed me he said it was weird
他給我看他說這很奇怪
why is this so thin
這個怎麼這麼薄
I can't see it
我一看不得了
this is a human skull
這是人頭骨
so i immediately
所以我那時候我馬上
I'll hug the plastic bag quickly
我就和塑膠袋趕快抱起來
I said this place
我說這個地方啊
cover it up
趕快把它蓋起來
I will invite the captain of the army
我就請那個軍方的隊長
Captain Zhang now has Lieutenant Colonel Shao Xiaosheng
張隊長現在有少孝生中校了
What about him
他呢
I said hurry up and try to find a way to make it
我說趕快盡量想辦法把它
this one
這一塊啊
You get a plastic sheet or something to cover the bag
你弄個塑膠布什麼把包蓋起來
I must come to work again
我一定要來再工作
that this is the first time
那個這是第一次
Bright leads to discovery of human skull
亮導人頭骨的發現
that's how i found it
是這麼發現的
This, this, curator Pan, is there to pick
這個這個潘館長在那一摳
I said I can't pick anymore
我說還不能再摳了
just before
就放前
ok let's read the next chapter
好 我們再看下一章
Okay, this second story is
好 這個第二段故事就是
On the cliff, the fields are surrounded by flowers
懸崖上田野靠花絕
I'm probably going to tell you about the discovery of this plum group.
大概我要講一下這個李子群的發現
Bright Island Blossoms
亮島花絕
His cultural background is also Liangdao Neng No. 1 massive brother
他的文化情況還有亮島能一號海量哥
I mistakenly called it Brother Hailiang
我把它錯號叫海量哥
Maybe Brother Hailiang in the future
也許海量哥以後說不定
How is it better educated than his number one
比他的一號怎麼更好教育
maybe more colloquial
也許會更通俗
Let's see below
我們來看下面
Thanks
謝謝
ok at this point we'll decide
好 這時候我們就決定
It's cold at this time
這時候天氣很冷
it is this time
正是這個時候
it's cold in december
12月這時候天氣很冷
then we will
那我們就
This bed is not going
這個床也不走
The cot doesn't leave
小床也不走
very stormy
風浪很大
we must go up
我們一定要上去
what to do after that
那之後怎麼辦呢
county government our county magistrate
縣政府 我們縣長
a lift
就安排了支升機
This is probably archeology
這是大概考古學
I am afraid that archeology in Taiwan is the first
恐怕在台灣考古學是第一次
In summer, I also want to be a senior machine
夏天也要做資深機器
this is probably the first time
這是大概第一次
this at the airport
這個在機場的時候
Shi Lingguang
石陵光
Called back now
現在已經調回來了
The director of the battle department is now
陣仗部主任現在是
Dean of Brigade Students
陣仗學員院長
he sent us this
他送我們這個
We are going to measure
我們要去量導
let's see below
我們看看下面
The following is the video
下面這個是把那個影片
Let's just say
我們下面就是說
Let's take a look
讓大家看一下
this our this
這個我們這個
senior machine
做的資深機
it's been a long time
就到本來很長
The video is relatively long, I fried it into
影片比較長我把它煎成
30 seconds a few seconds
30秒幾秒
Just look at this guide
就是看這個量導的這個
the form is like this
形式就是這樣子
This is
這是
It's this senior aircraft landing pad
它的這個資深機起落場
senior airport
資深機場
There is a road in the middle
在中間有一條路就是
actually the central road
事實上是中央道路
What about the plane?
那飛機呢我們
When it gets there first it flies around first
先到那裡的時候它先飛一圈
land after one lap
一圈以後再降落
Here's a clip of us sitting on the senior plane
這是我們坐在資深飛機上面的一段影片
this is where we are
這是我們在座
I just forgot to introduce
我剛才忘了介紹
We also have members of Liangdao archaeological team here.
我們在座還有量島考古隊的隊員
Taken by Mr. Yin Yizhi
吟義志先生拍的
This amount of island is like this
這個量島就這樣子
just such a small island
就這麼一個小島
very small island
非常小的一個島
Only 0.37 square kilometers
只有0.37平方公里
We are sitting on the senior plane in this plane
這個飛機我們就坐在資深飛機
we went first
我們先過去了
Now we're slowly descending
現在我們慢慢的要降落
don't land
不要降落
one of the following videos
下面的一个影片
because when we can
因为我们能去的时候
Let's go first and get the full
我们赶快先去再把全面
where are we going to work
我们要做工作地点什么
let's test it first
我们先考它一遍
At this time our tool
这时候我们的工具
Only gold luck left
只剩会金运不了
We have nineteen boxes of tools
我们有十九厢的工具
I packed a family of small fish boats with a scoop
就包了一家一勺小小的鱼船
just go up
就上去
you can watch it roar
你可以看它的轰浪
wait a minute to see
等一下可以看
This fella Bin
这个晾倒的阿彬哥们
how do they go at this pier
他们怎么样去在这个码头
almost every time
几乎每一次
Three or two days a scoop boat
三两天一勺船
one scoop boat a week
一礼拜一勺船
His carrier says they all have to work so hard
他的运布说他们都要这么辛苦
this pier is
这个码头是
The current military light is very, very difficult
这个现在的军光是非常非常难当的
the vice captain
这个副队长
The captain without the vice-captain is the leader
队长不带副队长是领头
The vice-captain is going to fight
副队长要打前仗
to play forward
要打前锋
all on top
都在上面
We are affected by the sea less often
我們受海水少來少去
in this way
這樣子
This is our pregnant stuff
這是我們的孕婦的東西
business case
的商案
The second is Mayor Fukushima
第二位是福島長
David Fukushima
衛福島長
so now
所以現在
Now the army has to be born first
現在軍隊都要生先世足
very hard
很辛苦的
This one is wearing black and this one is the vice-captain
這個穿黑衣服這一位是副隊長
Captain was not on the island at that time
那個時候隊長不在島上
Thanks
謝謝
So go through the plug
所以要经过塞
we're afraid things will be missed
我们怕东西会漏掉
You can see them all
可以看他们都在
Here
在这边
Fighting against the waves
跟海浪搏斗的样子
Okay, thank you
好,谢谢
let's go on
我们再接下去
ok then we are on the next one
好,那么我们就在下一张
This is luck
这个就是运补
Then when we start going up
那么我们开始上去的时候
Later we were here again
后来我们又在这个地方
we found the second place
我们就发现第二地点
Third place
第三地
Fourth place Third place
第四地點 第三地點
We later found four more locations
我們後來又發現四個地點
Of course the first location is the best
當然以第一個地點為最好
is the earliest
就是時代最早
second a little later
第二點稍微晚一點
The second location is more than 7,000 years old
第二地點有七千多年
this is the second place
這個是第二地點
The situation at the second location
第二地點的情況
this can be seen
這可以看出來
The back of the city piled here, the back of the master
這背城堆的這裡的背主
let's see the next one
我們再看下一張
This is the so-called backmaster
這就是所謂的背主
piled up here
這層堆的這裡
here are some
這裡頭有一些
This is a stone tool
這個就是石器
ok let's see the next one
好 我們看下一張
At this time we are digging
這時候我們在挖
So we're on this cliff
原來我們在這懸崖上面
only this rope
只有這條繩子
Then our rope
那麼我們這條繩子
who dares to work on it
誰敢在上面工作
the military said
軍方就說
All you soldiers, you go up
你所有阿兵哥你上去
Just wear a belt around your waist
就腰上要綁個腰帶
Hook the hook on this rope lock
把鉤子鉤在這個繩鎖上
I said it's not okay
我說這不行
Neither can our people
我們的人也不能夠
Wear a belt every day
天天綁個腰帶在身上
what to do
怎麼辦
Quickly, the military added three lines to form a net
趕快軍方就補了三條變成一個網
this is much safer
這個安全很多
Then this lady originally Suppose
那這位女士原來Suppose
Shouldn't just wear protective clothing
不應該就把防護衣就穿起來
Because why are you looking for protective clothing?
因為為什麼找防護衣
because we are afraid
就是因為我們怕
This is also our first archeology in Taiwan
這也是我們台灣考古的第一次
We are afraid that when we go to dig up this human bone
我們怕這個去挖這個人骨的時候
we will pollute that
我們會污染到那個
DNA from that skeleton
那個骨骸的DNA
In the future, DNA will say pollution
以後DNA會說污染的話
inaccurate
做不準的
For example, if it's my bunny girl
比如說假如是我的兔妹
i'm talking now
我現在在講話
Running out is someone Chen's DNA
跑出來是陳某人DNA
no joke
不笑話不大了
right
是吧
So we prepared 20 sets of protective clothing
所以我們就準備了20套防護衣
It's so cold that the temperature is only 6 degrees to 8 degrees
它冷到溫度只有6度到8度
Digging on this side of this cliff
在這個懸崖這個邊邊在挖
unbearably cold
冷得受不了了
So put on a set of protective clothing first
所以防護衣先拉一套穿一穿
this is such a story
這是這樣子一個故事
Then we'll have to plug all the lone walkers we dug up.
那麼我們挖出來的獨步器都要塞
our measurement
我們這個測量
field survey
現地測量
this
這個
this hot pit
這個燙坑
our location
我們位置
it's all on a cliff
這都在懸崖上
so the topic
所以題目
This is not an exaggeration at all
這個一點都不誇張吧
Considerations on the cliff
懸崖上的考慮
ok let's see what happens next
好我們再看下場
well this is our job
好這個是我們的工作
If this man's skull is dug here
這個人頭骨在這裡挖的話
let's go first
我們就先
save it here first
先把它保存在這裡
Others are pitting us
其他我們坑啊
main hope not to be shattered
主要的希望不要打下
broken edge
破壞的邊
So we dig like this
所以我們這樣子挖
Layer by layer
一層一層
This pit is dug layer by layer
這坑一層挖
dug out
挖出來的東西
stuff up no matter what
不管什麼東西都要塞
Apple stuffed
蘋果塞
let's see what happens next
我們再看下場
Well, of course there is a lot of congestion.
好當然有很多過塞啊
We have to pick things out
我們東西要挑出來啊
After the things are picked out, they need to be classified
東西挑出來以後還要分類
still have to take
還要拿去
go to that
去那個
support weight
撐重
wrap up
包起來
this is me
這是我
I have to work too
我也要工作
well watch the next one
好再看下一場
This is unearthed pottery
这个是出土的陶片
Many of these pottery pieces are scientific and cultural
这个陶片有很多是科化文
Of course there are many of them and Zi Jiawen
这当然有很多还有紫加文
Violet Gavin
紫加文
according to these things
依照这些东西看了
and this cabbage
还有这个菜头
so a little bit
所以稍微往一点的
So it's Kushidai only from
所以它的夸食代一只从
probably at the earliest
最早大概
Because our strata did the first time Taiwan University did it in 7900
因为我们地层做第一次台大做的是7900年
the earliest should be
最早应该是
This formation is 7900 years old
这个地层是7900年
But the human bones are under this layer
但是人骨是在这层的下面
So it's earlier 8300 to 8000 a
所以它更早8300到8000一
such a formation
这样一个地层
Then the above point is about 7500
那么上面一点的大概是7500的样子
This stratum is like this
这个地层是这样的
let's look at the next level
我们看下一层
This is the lover of its pottery
这个是它的陶片的情人
its sherds
它的陶片
this is a harpoon
这个是鱼叉
What about the harpoon?
鱼叉呢
it this harpoon is a thrown harpoon
它这个鱼叉是抛出去的鱼叉
after throwing it out
抛出去以后
There's a small harpoon in the back
后边有个小鱼叉
this rope
這個扳的繩子
Most are broken
大部分都斷掉
why?
為什麼呢?
the fish broke
魚一掙扎斷了
the rest of the head
剩下這個頭上的部分
we can see below
我們可以看下面
This is a complete harpoon
這個是一個完整的魚叉
In our Yangxian long special preference
在我們陽線長特別喜好
We will hold the national treasure in the future
我們以後要抱國寶
Qingnian
大清年
chicken vertebrae of this fish
這個魚的雞椎骨
bone
骨頭
bone needle
骨針
let's see below
我們看下面
Its stone tools are more primitive
它的石器就比較原始
In fact, the traces of typing are not very clear.
其實打字的痕跡不是很清楚
Mostly sourced locally
大部分都就地取材
Because why do we call it a stone tool
因為我們為什麼要說它是石器
because it has this tall trace
因為它有這個很高大的痕跡
through usable stone
就是經過能用的石頭
To become a stone tool
才能成石器
what can be made
能做出來的東西
this blade cloth
這個刃布
Damaged loss by all use
用都用損壞的損掉
let's see below
我們看下面
Thanks
謝謝
At this time, we discovered that we found here
這時候我們發現原來發現這裡
we keep it covered
我們一直蓋著它
we keep this piece
我們把這一塊留著
At this time we have a thought
這時候我們有個思考
just don't know
就到底不知道
i know the human skull is in this place
我知道人頭骨在這個地方
After all, the human body was dug out
到底人的身體是被挖掉了
has been dug up
已經被挖掉了
Still hiding in this stick
還是還藏在這個木杖裡面
So let's just keep this one
所以我們就把這一塊先留著
After the above is cleaned up
上面都清理好以後
Let's get back to the stick problem
我們再開始處理這個木杖的問題
So I slowly cleared up this part
所以才慢慢清這一部分
let's see below
我們看下面
Clear it out and dig it down slowly
清出來慢慢挖下去
It's such a level
清出來是這樣一個層面
It turns out that reproduction is inside
原來生殖是在裡面
it's the rod of exorcism
它是驅之杖
I have another story to tell at this point
這一點我要講另外一個故事
because we found out later
因為我們發現以後
I will ask
我就去問以前在馬祖量島
Friends of Fuguo Bingyu
福果冰玉的朋友
Do you have any I want to hear their stories
到底你们有没有我想听他们的故事
An instructor who is still in Huanian High School
现在还在花年高中的一位教官
Lieutenant Colonel Qin Huaian
叫做秦怀安中校
He said that long ago his Abbiers kissed the head of the side
他说老早他的阿彬尔斯上亲的边首
once dug up the human bones of three sentences
曾经挖了三句的人骨
Two sentences are for adults and one sentence is for children and babies
两句是成人的 一句是小孩儿 婴儿的
An adult kneels like this
一位成人都这样跪着
He suspected that at that time it was probably the old Communist
他怀疑那时候大概是老共牵壁人
So those people are kneeling and pushed into the sea
所以那些人都跪着 都推到海里去了
So this is destined, chairman
所以这个有缘吧 主委
Do you think if he found out then
你想他假如那时候发现
Then it won't be our turn
那时候就也轮不到我们的
Such
这样的
good
好
Then when we dig out this curiosity
那这时候我们挖出这一个奇心的时候
I will delete it with our team
我就跟我们团队去删良了
I said it's so cold
我说天气这么冷
If this thing is cleared up now
这个东西假如现在一清的话
all each
全部每一个都
The bones must be broken and broken, and so early
骨头一定会碎会坏 连带那么早
I said we better ship it back
我说我们最好把它运回去
this can't move now
这个不能够现在不能动
And once this is cleared up
还有这个一清出来以后
able to flash
能够一定闪的
There is no way to look like you can
能的样子什么样子是没办法
there's no way you can't fight back
你没办法再也斗不回去了
OK, we decided to dig
好 我们决定就挖
So just dig a piece
所以就挖就挖一块
wrap it up
把它包起来
After wrapping it up we dig
把它包起来以后 我们就挖
Dig a piece and transport it back to Nangan
挖一块就运回南干去
Folklore Museum to deal with slowly
民俗文物馆去慢慢处理
let's see the next one
我们看看下一张
this time is very difficult
这时候很大的艰难
except outside digging at the bottom
除了外面挖在底
You have to dig out the set list first and put it in first.
还要先慢慢挖套榜先套进去
to be able to drag the whole thing out
才能够把整个拖出来
So we wrap it tight and just do it
所以我们包得紧紧的把它就这么做
Pull it out and put it in the box later
以后拖出来又放在箱子里
transport it back to nangan
把它运回南干
let's take a look
我们看一下
Zhuanxiang
專鄉
Oh, this boat came back to Nangang
喔 這個座船回到南岡來的
just shipped it back
就把運回來了
ok let's see below
好 我們看下面
Oh, this is about the third
喔 這個講到第三個
This Liangdao man
這個亮島人
Fortunately, Brother Hailiang belongs to Heshui people
也好這個海亮哥的是河水人
his age
他的年代
how do we guess
我們怎麼猜啦
Just pull his sleeping rib
就拉他的一段睡的肋骨
make carbon stone firm
去做碳石石堅定
So guess it is
所以猜出來是
He is the BG of plus or minus 40 years in 738
他是七三八年加減四十年BG
His because of correction
他的因為要校正
All carbon stones must be calibrated
所有碳石都要校正
The correction result is 8320 to 8060
校正結果是8320到8060
BP on B4 Pleasant
BP 就B4 Pleasant
is huge gold
是巨金
is modern
是現代
Ten years old is around 8300 to 8300
十歲是8300到8300左右
His inspection of us. This is the third paragraph we are going to talk about.
他的考察我們這是第三段我們要講的
ok, let's see
好 先看下面
Oh, this one is back at the Matsu Literary and Art Museum
喔 這個回到了馬祖文藝書文物館
let's see next
我們再看下面
his clean up
他的清理
let's see below
我們看下面
this time we start
這時候我們開始
just find another team
就找另外一個團隊
As for Dr. Qiu Honglin from the Institute of Anthropology of Tsinghua University
就清華大學人類學研究所的這個邱弘林博士
he is an assistant professor
他是助理教授
He came to clean the bone
他來清理這個人骨
he slowly cleans up
他慢慢地清理
I rented this dirt and slowly peeled it off
我租成的把這個泥土慢慢一點點把它剝開
ok let's see the next one
好,我們看下一張
This is what it looks like when you peel it off
這剝出來就初步就是這個樣子
It's all a phenomenon of driving obstacles
都完全是驅之障的現象
let's see the next one
我們再看下一張
At this time we are going to take pictures and draw pictures
這個時候我們要拍照畫圖
it is like this
它就是這個樣子
Now, we
現在我們
we are talking about
我們在講下面
let's see next
我們再看下面
The picture drawn is like this
畫出來的圖是這樣的
This is the picture of the car
這是車面的圖
let's see below
我們看下面
its probably male
它大概男性
Number 1 is male
1號是男性
Around 30 years old
30歲左右驅之障
go outside without armor
沒有戰具就外面
no coffin
沒有棺材
What about the possession? I didn't find it.
那個占品呢 沒有發現
Up to the first time
到第一次的時候上面啊
each piece is so big
每一塊很這麼大的
History of the 20 cm diameter
20公分直徑的歷史
it's interesting
這一點很有意思的
Because not long ago we were in
因為前沒多久我們所裡啊
hold an international seminar
舉行一個國際研討會啊
An archaeologist from Vietnam came
越南的有一位考古學家來
he reports
他報告
from their place
他們那個地方的
There are also a group of district executives
也是區執障有一批
But much more than our time
但是比我們時代往很多
He said they had a piece of history on their rods
他說他們的牧杖上面都用一塊歷史
There's a piece of history all over it
都有一塊歷史蓋著上面
so is there some connection
所以是不是有一些關聯
we are still doing research
我們現在還在做研究
what about this person
那這個人呢
He is not a secondary account for the primary account
的一次賬他不是二次賬
lump sum
一次賬
the overall performance
那整體的表現出狀
Mouth ancient ah
口古啊
Everything in this world is more flowery
這個世之都很比較花達
Spade-shaped incisors are characteristic of Mongolians
產型門齒是蒙古種人的特徵
in this way
這樣子
Then he probably because of his dead ancient cut collection
那麼他大概因為他的作古大切集
deeper angle
角度比較深
He was identified as male Xu Zhizhan
他判定为男性徐之战
probably like this
大概是这样子
let's see the next one
我们看下一张
There's some left
还有一些
Height is about 160 or so
身高差不多160左右
That
那
It looks like 158, 160
差不多在158、160的样子
so not very tall
所以个子不是很高
and some diseases
还有一些疾病
let's see the next one
我们看下一张
he marked this
他显著的这个
The bones are thicker
骨骼都比较粗壮
look at the next one
再看下一张
he has this
他有这个
spine
脊椎骨啊
have this arthritis problem
有这个关节炎的毛病
look at the next one
来看下一张
that has arthritis
那有关节炎
his teeth
他牙齿
This has
这个有
just bite
就是咬合的很
very that
很那个
Fragrance is very powerful
香膜的很厉害
Eat well
吃结实
This can be seen
這個都可以看出來
look at the next one
你看下一張
and ears
還有耳朵 耳種
What is the ear type like?
耳種是怎麼樣呢
I'm looking at the next one
耳種是在看下一張
modern man
耳種是現代人
Filling people's ears
充難人的耳朵
Hello E.
Servus E.
Japanese and Korean divers
日本 韓國這些海女們
Those who often dig their backs
經常去挖背的這些
divers
海女們充難者
will have this problem
都會有這個毛病
It can be seen that she is often active there
可見她經常在那裡活動
let's see the next one
我們再看下一張
when this is done
這個做出來的時候
The result of the repair is like this
修補的結果是這樣子
very important point
很重要的一點
We're going to do 3D image scanning
我們要做3D影像掃描
This is the Cultural Resources Bureau of the Ministry of Culture
這個是文化部文資局
Cultural Groups in Tainan
在台南的文化團體組
one of its teams came in
它的一個團隊就進來了
Why not to do 3D scanning
為什麼不要做3D掃描
because what i just said
因為我剛剛講的
If we take all the bones
假如我們把所有的骨頭
After opening the glass
都把玻璃開來以後
you can't fight back
你就鬥不回去了
Current Technology 3D Scanning
現在的技術3D掃描
It's you who made it to this extent
就是你做成這個程度
I would like to 3D scan after
我願3D掃描好以後
It will be like a printer in the future
以後就好像列印機一樣
Will restore it back later
以後會把它復原回去
just make a model
就做成模型
rely on this set of technology
就靠這一套技術
So we also made this set of techniques
所以我們也做了這一套技術
let's see the next one
我們看下一張
I forgot to say just now
剛才我忘了講
all the dots
所有的點點
It's their 3D scanning of this layout
就是他們3D掃描這個布點
later it will be corrected when
以後它會校正的時候
Rely on this point to correct
依靠這個點來校正
because you transform
因為你會變形
Sometimes this angle and so on will be deformed
時常這個角度等等會變形
it may depend on this drug to correct
它可能依靠這個藥物來校正
now let's see the next one
現在我們看下一張
The case of this 3D scan
這個3D掃描的情況
Do another 3D scan
再做3D掃描
look at the next one
再看下一張
This 3D scan means
這個3D掃描就是說
What I just said is mainly
我剛剛講的主要是
Reconstructing the circumstances of the burial
重建埋葬的情況
while doing
而做的
let's see the next one
我們看下一張
The fourth story is
第四個故事就是
Big brother
海量哥
The Discovery of Massive Girls in "Liangdaoren 2"
《亮島人2》海量妹的發現
this has many stories
這個有很多故事了
many stories
很多故事了
roughly like this
大致是這樣子
its discovery was providence
它的發現是天意
this is what we are all going to talk about
這我們都要講的
how old is it
它的年齡多少呢
Almost 7500-750
差不多7500-750
This is very accurate
這個很準了
This carbon word is very accurate
這個碳詞字做得非常準
this object
這個物
The material difference in the middle is only 30 years
這中間的物差只有30年
rather accurate
而非常準
Massive girls unearthed suffered setbacks
海量妹出土受到挫折
She used to be innocent
她曾經面目純非果
A survey of institutional anthropology
海量妹體制人類學的考察
let's see the next one
我們看下一張
Why is it God's will to say this?
為什麼是天意這樣講
when we decided
當時我們決定
When the position of the draped pit is determined
這個披上的坑的位置要定的時候
We have two different opinions on the team
我們就團隊裡頭就有兩種不同的意見
One opinion is that
有位意見就是說
30 meters long from this long
從長這麼長有30公尺
Don't focus too much on here
你這個不要多集中這裡
you should hit a place where you lose a little
你應該打一個輸一點的地方
Then my opinion is don't go too far
那我的看法就是不要離太遠
Because this place is the last
因為這個地方背成最後
thicker words
越厚的話
We may have more things
我們東西可能會越多
There are more piles
有堆積的越多
that's a compromise
那於是折中的辦法
As a result, I was 1 meter away from it
結果我就距離它距離1公尺
1 meter distance 1 meter
1公尺距離1公尺
this is a point
這是一個重點
let's see the next stop
我們再看下一站
then we have a little more
那我們還有一點
back to the front
就又回到前面
sorry we talked
對不起我們講了
still think about it
還有回想不想
i think it should be this
我覺得應該這個
We were originally 1 meter wide
我們原來是1公尺寬
I should be 1 meter 2
我應該打成1公尺2
because step aside
因為靠邊邊
But this side will be a little wider
但是這邊會稍微寬一點
So I think the bigger
所以我覺得這個越大
the bigger the better
越大一點越好
So add 20 centimeters to the next stop
所以就加20公分再看下一站
come out the result
出來結果
yes i didn't show off
對 我沒有受秀出來
we dug this hole
我們挖到這個坑
It turned out to be here
原來挖的就在這裡
Yes look at this position
對 看這個位置
This came out later
這個都後來 後來脫出來的
We originally dug the hole here
我們原來坑是挖到這裡
It's almost the end of the digging.
這個挖的時候已經快 快到底了
when it's almost over
快完了的時候
we are on our feet
我們居然在我們腳腳上
its lacquer bone was found
發現了它的漆蓋骨
So I know that the pit is here
所以知道 原來坑是在這裡
If this place is not clean
假如這個地方如果清的不乾淨
ignore the paintbone
忽略掉漆蓋骨
won't find it either
也不會發現到它
Later we dug after the painted bone
後來我們挖在漆蓋骨以後
we expand
我們就擴張了
I think it should expand from here
就覺得從這裡應該擴張出來
That's why I roughly merged them together.
所以才把就大致融合就出來了
This No. 2 pit looks like this
這個2號坑是這樣子
Number two, that's how the second child found out.
第二號 老二是這麼發現的
still so easy
還那麼容易
what we found
我們發現的
If it's us, we won't fight
要如果是我們坑不會打
Wolves won't notice it at all
狼一點點不會發現到它
And if we don't expand a little bit by 20 centimeters
還有我們如果不擴張一點點20公分
can't find it either
也發現不到它
This is a very fortunate thing
這個是非常慶幸的一件事
ok let's see the next one
好 我們再看下一張
alright
好了
The chairman may now find out
主委現在也許會發現到
There is something wrong with this picture
這一張圖片整個人有問題
what is the problem
什麼問題
its head
就是它的頭部
even the bones are gone
連骨都不見了
this is a story
這個是一段故事
Our county magistrate yang is coming
我們的楊縣長要上場
he will do
他要做
he wants to sigh
他要做真嘆
why
為什麼呢
because we were
因為我們那時候
when we dig
我們挖的時候
Because there was a typhoon at that time
因為那時候正好有颱風來
And our teacher Qiu has a class in Tsinghua University
還有我們的邱老師在清華有課
he has no time
他時間來不及
let's share
我們分享一下
can't finish this
這個要做完不行
So we found this eyeball
所以我們發現這個眼球
what is this eye socket
這個眼窩什麼
probably this person looks like
大概這個人樣子
The leg bones look like a little model
腿骨一點點模型樣子出來
We thought we shouldn't dig anymore
我們就覺得我們不應該再挖了
stop today
今天趕快停了
we'll come back next time
我們下支再來
Do it carefully, there is no time
仔細再做沒有時間了
another typhoon
又挖颱風
Let's smoke it back part of the way
我們就把它土煙回去一部分上面
Ma Dong, cover, cover, cover.
馬東一蓋一蓋蓋好
When we went back last four weeks
等我們上四個禮拜回去的時候
when we started digging
我們開始在挖的時候
Oops
糟了
All the bones are gone
臉骨全部不見了
At this time I am very anxious
這時候我自己非常急
how do i explain
我這怎麼交代
Because everyone can see clearly
因為各位可以大家明眼的一看
this is heartbreaking
這根本心破的
this is not the old look
這不是古老的樣子
how to explain this
這怎麼交代
very urgent
非常急
that's when we thought
那時候我們就想到了
there are three possibilities
有三個可能性
a man from the sea
一個在海上來的人
One is to bring an occasional person on the island from time to time
一個是時常在島裡頭帶個偶爾來的人
The third kind of friendship is that it must be a person who is resident on the island.
第三種情義就是一定是在常駐在島上的人
There is only Brother Bing on that island
那島上只有阿兵哥
So we make judgments on the spot
所以我們現場出現現場判斷
He said it must be from the island
他說一定是本島的人
Do not consider the first two of the three
三個前面的兩個都不要考慮
people from this island
就是本島的人
Because of this, I told the county magistrate
因為這樣子我就跟縣長說
I said if you change the range from that big
我說如果你把這個範圍原來從那麼大
at sea because we were digging
海上是因為我們在挖的時候
Wearing yellow trousers and changing in vain
穿著黃褲衣白白的換來換去
People who assume that the sea is the opposite shore must be curious
假想海上是對岸的人一定好奇
I don't know what the hell you're up to, let's go up and see
不曉得你在搞什麼鬼我們上去看看
this is our speculation
這是我們一種推測
It's impossible for us to say on the spot
我們現場說都不可能
must be from the island
就一定是島的人
Since I live on the island a lot, we know
因為我常住在島上,我們知道
Harbin and the officers are busy with his business all day and night
哈賓哥們跟軍官們一天到晚都在忙他的事
There is no time left to kill our specimens
沒有餘限功夫去亡我們的標本
And how can we pull out our face teeth
還有怎麼會把我們的臉部牙齒拔掉
This is not a medical staff, not familiar with medical treatment
這個不是醫務人員,不是熟悉醫療
People who are familiar with the structure of this human body will only do this kind of thing
熟悉這個人體的構造人只不會做這種事
We use his on the spot
我們現場就利用他的
I know, I know
知道了,知道了
Then he found it
後來他就把它找出來了
found out
找出來了
things are guaranteed
東西也保障
But right now because this is a military guy
但現在目前因為這是軍方人士
Still in scouting phase
目前還在偵察階段
I can't tell more about his story
我不便多講他的故事
All in all, we got him back as Omi-head
總而言之,我們把他找回來是歐米頭
I only have face to face today
我今天才有臉見人
I have the face to say this today
今天才有臉去講這個話
Otherwise I wouldn't be able to do this
要不然我不能夠做這個
I can't explain this
這個沒辦法交代
This is a very interesting story
這個是非常好玩的一段故事
a story
一段故事
found it
結果就找到了
Like this, let's see the next one
這樣子,我們再看下一張
Probably because of this gender
大概因為這個性別
It was because it hadn't been cleaned up at that time.
原來因為那時候還沒有清理乾淨
preliminary resistance
初步的抗法
I thought it was difficult
以為也是難的
It was difficult for us to announce the first time
我們那時候第一次公佈是難的
Then slowly clean him up
後來慢慢把他清理乾淨以後
Plus DNA sent to Germany
加上DNA送到德國去
Because the Germans have these two sentences of DNA
因為德國人這兩句DNA的
The back skirt of the mitochondria
這個立線體的當背群
all appeared
都出現了
number one is one
第一號是一
I will say later that the second number is 29
我等一下會講第二號是二九
all appeared
都出現了
Because both sentences are difficult
因為是兩句都是難的話
We just want to be a Y chromosome
我們就希望能夠做Y chromosome
Y Narsity DNA減定
Y Narsity DNA減定
As a result, the Germans were number one
結果德國人做第一號
do have
做有
His DNA has been extracted
已經抽到他的DNA
But the second number can't be drawn no matter what
但是第二號怎麼抽也抽不到
He later tested him and said he was female
他後來再檢驗他說他是女的
can't be a man
不可能是男的
Later, we consider institutional man as
後來我們再把體制人認為
The result of this careful examination
這個仔細檢驗結果
indeed a woman
確實是女的
So number two we
所以第二號我們才
Correction is female
糾正是女的
ok let's see below
好我們看下面
And he had a baby
而且他有生過孩子
that lady
那個女士
Then the case of number two
那麼二號這個情況
He has another one here
他這裡還有一隻
The stone ball stepped on his feet
石球踩到他的腳下
I don't know if it makes sense
不曉得有沒有意義
do not know either
也不知道
look at the next one
看下一张
Fu Yuancheng
那傅元成
this is really hateful
这个真是很恨
Great Faith of Disbelief
不信忠之大信
We are still so complete
我们居然还这么完整
its integrity
它的完整度
The physical integrity of the entire number two is 85% to 90%
整个第二号的体育完整度是85%到90%
this is machine difficulty
这是机器困难
it is 7500
它是7500年
Although it is 7500 years
虽说是7500年
but still so complete
但是还这么完整
this is machine difficulty
这是机器困难
so very happy
所以非常的庆幸
Thanks
谢谢
look at the next one
再看下一张
This is the comparison of No. 1 and No. 2
这是一号 二号对比
you see the face is a little different
你看脸部有点不同
the face is a little different
脸部有点不同
look at the next one
看下一张
these two groups
这两群
Roughly speaking in the group
群组中大概大致来说
it's very similar
它相似性很大
so it should
所以它应该
this is
这个是
is a regional person
是一个区域的人
On the other hand, number one is male
另外一方面就是一号是男的
number two is female
二号是女的
His face also shows his difference
他脸部也表现他的差异性
The third is that age is the same
第三个就是年龄什么也相当
Individuals who are all around 30 years old
都在30岁左右的个体
height or model situation
身高还是模型情形
he also has some differences
他也有一些差异
because of this aspect
因为这一方面
Today I also have some friends in molecular biology
今天也有一些分子生物方面的朋友
I am a layman
我这个是外行
to teach directly
要直教
Please teach directly
请直教
let's see the next one
我们再看下一张
The comparison of these two sentences is
这两句的人的比较就是
Of course number one and number two are men
当然一号跟二号一个是男性
one is female
一个是女性
one time at a time
一次是一次
he didn't
他都没有
are all pits
都是土坑
none occupied
都没有占据
no coffin
都没有棺材
Occupy and no soil hole
占据也没有土穴
he is the group
他是群之
Health group
养生群之
group like left car
像左车的群之
One is Naozhi
一个是养生直之
two are straight
两个是养生直之
towards the east
朝著正東
facing one to the left and one to the right
面向一個向左一個向右
No training items
培障品沒有
He has the poetry hammer just mentioned.
他這個底下有個剛才說的有個詩錘
Then there is a piece of what I just mentioned
那這個上面我剛剛講的有一塊
Is this a sign
這裡是不是做標誌
we are still doing research here
我們還在這裡做研究
What about number two?
那第二號這下面呢
It's a fire pit phenomenon
是有火塘的現象
What is the Huotang Phenomenon?
什麼叫火塘現象呢
there are people from before us
就是有我們以前的人
used to live here
曾經住在這裡
fire pit and live things
打火坑而住東西
was on that spot
曾經在那個地點上
I'll be angry later
後來會氣了
over there in the garbage dump
垃圾堆的那裡
ok let's see the next one
好我們再看下一張
The results of the DNA analysis
那這個DNA的分析的結果
that's because
就是因為
it's all
它是這個都
Approaching the modern Austronesian universe
接近現代的南島宇宙
This Hanshi seat
這個漢市座
It is similar to the South Island universe
它跟南島宇宙這個
high degree of similarity
相似性高度的相似
If the second analysis is reliable
第二個分析可靠的話
Daoist Liang may be
亮道人就有可能是
linguist preliminary design
語言學家初步設計
6000 years ago
距今6000年前
Before the Nandao Yu Clan started phase expansion
南道宇族開始相位擴張之前
Daoyu Ethnic Group Living in Yuannan, Southeast China
居於中國東南元南道宇族群
The result is
這個結果就是
Because its number one is 10,000 to 10,000 haplogroups
因為它第一號是1到1萬單倍群
The second number is haplogroup 290
第二號是290單倍群
It is similar to modern Taiwan, Yuanzhou, America, Philippines
它都跟現代的台灣元州美菲律賓
Indonesia, whole Luogang, Southeast Asia
印尼、整羅岡、東南亞
The Daoyu ethnic group has a matrilineal blood relationship
導宇族群有母系血緣的關係
But now the ethnic groups in the southeast of mainland China
但是現在中國大陸東南地區族群
very far from them
離他們非常遠
let's see the next one
我們看下一張
This is what I am very cautious about
這個就是我非常慎重
Because in fact the identification of carbon current events
因為其實碳時事的鑒定
We have also done a lot in Taiwan
我們台灣也做了很多
This experience is also very rich
這個經驗也很豐富
For example, National Taiwan University has Guijunshu Experimental Center
比如說台大有貴軍書實驗中心
we first started
我們第一次開始
We send him to do whatever we carry
我們背什麼都送他做
very accurate
做得很準
It's all his 7900
都是他7900
that's on his upper floor
那個是在他的上層
So it's all right
所以都很準的
But I'm cautious
但是我為慎重起見
We can share the beta that I sent to the United States
我們這能股我送到美國的Beta
That is a very well-known international geography of carbon essence
那是國際非常有名的做碳實質的地理
So there's nothing wrong with taking his own ribs
所以我們取他本身的肋骨就沒有錯了
Because his own bones are made of carbon substance
因為他本身的骨頭去做碳實質
The result is
做出來的結果就是
This is 8320
這個是8320
What I just talked about goes all the way to 8160
剛剛講的一直到8160
two sigma
兩個Sigma
Two data come out
兩個數據出來
You can go to 806
往的可以往到806
this is
這個是
that's right
那另外對
this is the sentence
這個就是這句
I am making an example
我這個是弄個例子
our later
我們後來的
Energy stock
能股
The ancient DNA and some artifacts are given to Beta to make
不古的DNA還有一些器物都拉給Beta去做
although it is expensive
雖然它很貴
One costs more than 10,000 Taiwan dollars
一個要一萬多塊台幣
our next one
我們下一張
This is what we have to do with this
這是我們這個跟以此相關的
XIV and carbon XIV representatives
十四和碳十四年代的代表
For example, Inao
比如說這稻尾一
The first point is to say the first place
第一點就是說第一處
The second place The second place is between 7600 and 7500
第二處第二處就七千六到七千五之間
So much data in the first place
第一處就有這麼多數據
this is nogu
這是能古
two years old
兩二年古
Its culture has reached seventy-nine
它的文化程有到七千九的
almost seven thousand years
差不多都七千多年
Minmin Harbor is from 1638 to 1852 A.D.
百姓港這個是公元1638到1852年
this is the age
這是這個年代
let's see the next one
我們再看下一張
Then we will talk about the fifth paragraph of the story.
那就講到第五段的故事了
The fifth story is very important is the study of DNA
第五段故事很重要的就是DNA的研究
dna research
DNA研究
we were
我們我原來
My idea is how we should encourage our own domestic research teams
我的想法就是怎麼樣我們應該要鼓勵我們國內自己的研究團隊
I hope to find a partner in China
我希望在國內去找一個合作的夥伴
But then I inquired about the result
但後來我打聽了結果
The success rate of domestic partners is not high, about one-tenth
國內的夥伴成功率不高大概十分之一
Send ten to make one
送十個做一個
They doubt everything about his accuracy
他這個準確性什麼他們都懷疑
I was thinking that we only had this sentence, then there was only number one
我在想我們只有這一句那時候只有一號
what to do
那怎麼辦
1 out of 10 this can't risk these
十分之一的話這不能冒這些
I will listen more
我就多聽打聽
that's very lucky
那非常的幸運
This is my colleague, Academician Zhang Zhenghua
這個我的同事張政華院士
He happened to be with Germany's Max Plan
他正好跟德國的Max Plan
With Professor He Yingqing, the vice president of Kaohsiung Medical University at that time
跟我們那時候的高雄醫學大學的副校長跟應清教授
he is in contact with him
他跟他在聯繫
Another day I called him and asked about the domestic DNA
還有一天我打電話給他說問這個國內DNA
Because he said this for a long time, tomorrow, Principal Ge will take his son
因為他說這個很久我明天這個葛校長會帶他的公子
It is his son, President Ge’s son, Mr. Ge Mingxuan, who is a doctoral student at Max Plan in Germany
就是他的公子葛校長的公子葛明軒先生是在德國的Max Plan做讀博士
I'm about to graduate now, and I happen to be a doctoral student there.
現在要快畢業了正好在那做博士生
He also made Taiwan's DNA of Taiwan's aborigines
他也做台灣的DNA台灣原住民的
I think this opportunity is too rare for me, so I hurried to Tainan to meet them
我想這個機會太難得我所以趕快趕到台南跟他們會合
Once they are of course more interested in the 8000+ years
一旦他們當然是對8000多年興趣更大了
Because there are more specimens in Nanke, he has 2000 sentences
因為南科的標本多他有2000句
But South Kota's earliest is 4800
但是南科他最早的是4800
Of course he is most interested in the earliest us of more than 8,000 years
最早的我們8000多年他當然興趣最大
so take priority
所以就優先
This Max Plan, this location is world famous
這個Max Plan這個地點他是世界有名的
Let's see the next one now
這個我們現在看下一張
I'll talk about us later
我等一下再講我們
Follow Principal Ge, Vice Principal Ge
是跟著葛校長 葛副校長
He is now the president and vice president of China Medical University
他現在是中國醫藥大學校長 副校長
This Professor Gu Yinqing, I am with them.
這個格印青教授 我跟他倆一起
His wife accompanied us to Germany
他的夫人陪我們去德國
Send my sample to this institute in person
把我的sample親自送到這個研究所去
let's see the next one
我們看下一張
This is the Stone King Professor Stone King
這個就是這個Stone King Professor Stone King
He is their director
他呢 就這是他們的主任
This and that ethnography this crew
這個那個人種學這個機組人
This is the vice principal's son
這個是副校長他的公子
and his team
還有他的團隊
then i go for the first time
那我第一次去
Of course I'm going to do a briefing
當然我要做一個簡報
Do a briefing with them for a photo shoot
做一個簡報跟他們拍的照片
But now I want to introduce this Stone King in particular
但我現在要特別介紹這位Stone King
our partners
我們的夥伴
He's just waiting for what I'm going to say
他就是等一下我要講的
this is who we are now
這個我們現在的人
our current race
我們現在的人種
Not at all Homo Sapiens Sapiens
根本不属于Homo Sapiens Sapiens
Homo sapiens sapiens
Homo Sapiens Sapiens
His theory is out of Africa
他的理论就是出非洲的理论
That is, his ancestors changed from Elsang to Africa
就是他的祖先是从Elsang变成除了非洲以后
Follow M and N
跟M跟N
The theory out of Africa
出非洲的这理论
He was published by Professor Stone King and his teacher
他就是Stone King教授跟他的老师发表的
Now no one doubts his academic
现在没有人怀疑他的学术
Because the race is very...
因为人种非常...
This science is that everyone is very...
这个学术是大家都很...
That is to say, between them
就是怎么说他们同行之间啊
It's all very clear
都是非常明了的
So he is a very important scholar who came up with African theory
所以他是出非洲理论的一个很主要的学者
so we're glad he's working with us
所以我们很庆幸他跟我们合作
and his son
还有他公子
This lady is surnamed Fu
这位女士是姓傅
Fu Qiaomei
傅乔妹
Ms. is mainland China
女士是中国大陆
Graduate students in Beijing
北京區的研究生
He is now a graduate
他現在他一畢業
If the distance is low, pull it to Harvard University and grab it immediately
跌距低一拉到哈佛大學馬上搶到去
snatch him away
馬上把他搶走
now at harvard
現在在哈佛大學
So he is the master of our DNA extraction
所以他是主要我們DNA萃取
he did it all
都是他做的
he arrived last christmas
他到去年的聖誕節
he won't go back to beijing
他不回北京
He said I dedicated my tribute to your DNA
他說我專門為你DNA感貢
yes do this
對 來做這個事
ok let's see the next one now
好 我們現在看下一張
At this time, I put this sample
那這時候我把這個sample
In the beginning he asked for a leg bone
開始的時候他要求是一個腿骨
this straight bone
這個直骨
this tooth
這個牙齒
Three things to send to the deputy doctor
三件東西送去這副副博士
he accepts our specimens
他接受我們的標本
let's see the next one
我們看下一張
good
好
The result of his analysis is
他分析的結果就是
this we just saw
這個我們剛才看過了
said he was
講過他是
one is 1
一個是1
Number one is the 10,000 to 10,000 haplogroup
第一號是1到1萬單倍群
Haplogroups, let me explain a bit more
單倍群我要再解釋一下
So haplogroups are Multiconscience
所以单倍群就是Multiconscience
The Hypergroup
这个Hypergroup
It's because of the DNA in our body
它是因为我们人体里面的DNA
Each DNA trap has 23 pairs of blue bodies
每一个DNA困值有23对的蓝色体
23 pairs inside
23对里面
22 pairs are all XX
22对都是XX
Only one pair is XY
只有一对是XY
Only the blue sex can have the appearance of Y
是只有蓝性才有Y的出现
If it is female, it is still XX
假如女性的话还是XX
so in other words
所以换句话说
Inside each set of DNA
每一组的DNA里面
23 pairs of blue body inside
23对蓝色体里面
45/46 is X
46分之45是X
1/46 of only one blue sex is Y
只有一个蓝性的46分之1是Y
So 1 is also in other words
所以1也换句话说
it is more
它比较多
So it's easier for him to do
所以他做的比较容易
So first make it like this
所以先做出来是这样子
The second sentence is the R9 haplogroup
第二句是R9单倍群
From these two sentences
从这两句里
He is with R1 and R9
他都跟R1跟R9
They are all related to Taiwanese aboriginal returning soldiers with matrilineal blood relationship
都跟台湾原住民回头兵有母系血缘的关系
but how much
但是几少
There are very few people in mainland China
我们中国大陆的人群是非常少
let's see the next one
我们看下一张
This is the L3 just mentioned
这个就是刚刚讲的L3
When the M comes out
M开出来的时候
N is mainly
N主要是
Most of Europe is N
欧洲大部分是N
M go from here
M从这里走
I have always been in mainland China
一直我中国大陆
Then M looks like this
那么M是这样子的
There are also parts of N that go to the coastline very early
N也有部分很早就走海岸线
all the way to australia
一直到澳洲
Then the M branch goes all the way to America
那M这一支一直到美洲
let's see the next one
我们看下一张
Our E is here
我们的E是在这里
That is when M came out and Tuhuizhou came out and developed to this generation of M9.
就是M出來 土匯州出來有發展到這一代M9的時候
M9 comes out of D probably in this place
M9脫出D大概在這個地方
So sentence D is this group
所以D句是這群
The second sentence we have to see the next one
那第二句我們要看下一張了
The second sentence is N becomes R
第二句是N變成R
R9 is in this place
R9是在這個地方
It is this generation that is Tibet, the generation of Izzy Indochina Peninsula
就是這一代就是西藏啊 伊茲中南半島這一代
I am also a layman
這個我也是外行
so please advise
所以請指教
Thank you, let's look at the next question
謝謝 我們再看下一題
This is from L3 from here on M
這個就是從L3從這裡開始M
We E are this group
我們E是這群
So R9 is the N group
所以R9是N這群
to this group
對 這群
Let's look at the next question
我們再看下一題
this what i'm going to talk about now
這個我現在要講的這個
this
這個
epilogue
結語
Well, since this Liangdao man was unearthed
那么从这个亮岛人出土以后
we are discussing now
我们现在在讨论
what problems did he cause
他到底引起了哪些问题
this is my personal opinion
这是我个人的看法
there are nine questions
有九个问题
The first is to reinforce the theme of the ocean in ancient China
第一个就是加强人士中国上古时代海洋的主题
how do you say that
这话怎么说
Just because China includes Taiwan
就因为我们中国包括台湾
At the earliest, all historians focused on the Central Plains
最早所有史学家都把眼光放在中原
study that place
都研究那个地方
The regions on our frontier seem to be understudied
我们边疆的地区好像研究得很少
very few
非常少
This is the difference between a mainstream and some fringe research
这个是一个主流跟一些边缘的研究之不同
In fact, people from Liangdao more than 8,000 years ago
那其实由亮岛人八千多年前
he is at sea
他就海上
We can know that
我们可以知道
In fact, it was very early on the edge of the continent in East Asia
其实很早就在东亚这一带大陆边缘
early
老早
Sea nations have been active for a long time
早就有海洋民族一直在活动之中
This is what we have been ignoring before
这个是我们以前一直忽略的
Then this year
那今年啊
From 2030
2030年来
already started now
已经现在开始
Many of us have started to notice this
我们已经很多人开始重视到这一点
aspects like archeology
像考古学的方面
archeology too
考古学也是
Because it used to be dominated by the Central Plains
因为以前一直都是以中原为主
Everything Central Plains
什么都中原
even our predecessors
即使是我们的前辈
our teachers
我们的老师辈
Mr. Zhang Guangzhi
这个张光志先生
His research is still in the Central Plains
他的研究还是中原
For example, his Longshan Luowei
比如说他的这个龙山罗尾
second category
第二类
It is the school during the trip to Yongsan
就是龙山行程期的学所
He is from Longshan Culture
他还是龙山文化过来
This coastal generation is all descended from the Longshan travel period.
这个沿海这一代都是龙山行程期下来的
And then until the 1980s
那后来一直到1980年代
start
开始
In the history of China, there were mainland scholars with strange book handles.
在中国历史时候有大陆学者书柄奇
He thinks Chinese history is not like this
他就认为中国历史不是这样
He broke the concept
他就打破这观念
Think that there should be six cultural regions in Chinese history
认为中国历史应该是有六个文化区
There are six cultural districts in Geju Frontier
格举边疆有六个文化区
In fact, the six cultural districts were all developed at the same time
其实六个文化区当时都同时发展
Later, slowly because the Central Plains culture is too strong
到了后来慢慢的因为中原文化太强
too powerful
势力太强势
So slowly contact more and more
所以慢慢的接触越多越多
contact them
才跟他们接触
you just know something
你才有一些认识
this is mr book handle
这是书柄奇先生的
Of course, our Mr. Zhang Guangzhi also later
当然我们张光之先生也后来
Because this trend also has some changes
因为这趋势也有一些改变
so I always just because
所以我始终就因为
Later, when I did research on marine guide reputation for me,
我后来给我搞海洋导誉研究的时候
I feel that these ethnic groups should have been earlier
我感觉的其实应该老早这些民族
It's not because they've been around the coast for a long time
不是因为老早他们就在沿海一带
float around, walk around, walk around
飄來飄去走來走去
So the inland culture is completely different from the ocean culture
那麼內陸文化跟海洋文化是完全不同的
concept is different
觀念是不一樣的
Because the inland cultures are enclosed in one piece
因為內陸文化一塊地圈起來
its resource is the land
它的資源就是那塊地
So everyone has to tell the truth and I will talk more.
所以一直大家要理真我多去講
the ocean is not
海洋不是
The ocean because the sky outside them is too wide
海洋因為他們外面天物太闊了
so they are drifting
所以他們是漂流的
relatively large liquidity
流動性比較大
This is their characteristic is that they are different from the inland
這是他們的特點是跟內陸不一樣
and their inland culture
還有他們內陸文化
Because the resources are there
因為資源在那邊
they are ac
他們是交流
Foreign exchanges have long existed
對外交流老早就有的
have been communicating with each other for a long time
老早就是互相的交流
So oceanic culture
所以海洋性的文化
And inland culture
還有內陸文化
It slowly develops into steak
它慢慢才發展成steak
nation
國家
Nation into country
民族成國家
Because it wants to govern the oceanic nation of this land
因為它要治理這塊地海洋性的民族
Not easy to become State
不容易變成State
it's not easy
它不容易
because it's inherently fluid
因為它本來就流動流動
I'm not very good at staying in a certain place
自己不太會沉住在某一個地方
how will it develop
會發展怎麼樣
looking at the land
是看著那塊地
big no
大不是
So Oceanic Networks
所以海洋性的網絡
like us in taiwan
就像我們台灣
why such a big island
為什麼這麼大一個島
is there any country
有沒有國家
no since ancient times
自古沒有
We arrived at the Han people a little earlier than Zheng Chenggong
我們到漢人比鄭成功早一點
It is now more than four hundred years ago
現在距今四百多年了
when come
來的時候
Taiwan is still mostly aborigines
台灣還是大部分都是原住民
many tribes
都是好多個部落
come here to live together
來這裡活在一塊
it lives here
它就住在這裡
It is not easy to become State
它是不容易成State
This is where the ocean is different
這是海洋不同的地方
So I think it's time to be afraid
所以我是覺得上過時恐怕
ocean population
我們要把海洋族群
Research on this aspect must be strengthened
方面的研究必須要加強
the second
第二個
Of course, because we studied
當然因為以前我們研究
The prehistoric cultural sequence along the Mijiang coast
這米江沿海一帶的史前文化序列
Their earliest was Ke Qiutou
他們最早的是柯秋投
Fujian Pingtang
福建平堂
Ke Qiu voted that his age would not exceed seven thousand years
柯秋投他的年代不會超過七千年
Now if we assume Liangdao people
現在我們假如亮島人
This is eight thousand and seven thousand words
這個是八千年七千多的話
to break their sequence
要打破他們的序列
I'm afraid to be in their
恐怕要在他們
This Liangdao culture was earlier than them
這個亮島文化要在他們之前更早
this is the third
這是第三個
Chronology of divergence of the origin of the Austronesian universe
南島宇宙起源地分化的年代
because
因為
The main committee may understand
主委要也許可以了解
so-called universe
所謂的宇宙
because the universe's two
因為宇宙的兩個
how is the universe
宇宙是怎麼樣
I tell you something in common
我跟你講共同的話
i can communicate
我可以溝通的
such a group
這麼一群
But it doesn't mean
但是呢不表示
Bloodborne is the bloodline of the unified race
血源是统一族的血源
at this point
这一点
so we can see
所以我们可以看
You can tell from the two sentences of Liangdao
从亮岛这两句人骨就知道
One sentence is one one
一句是一一嘛
One sentence is twenty nine
一句是二九嘛
where did twenty nine come from
二九是哪里来的
what i just said
我刚才讲的
it is from indochina peninsula from burma
它是从中南半岛从缅甸
Inner Belt of Tibet and Burma
西藏缅甸内带
Exhibition to Indochina Peninsula
划展到中南半岛
Just arrived in the southern ocean area
才到南方海洋这一带
One is from the M9 in Mainland China
一是中国大陆的从M9出来的
It turned out to be in this area
是原来就在这一带
So to express two sentences we found
所以表示两句我们发现的
already two different groups
就已经是不同两个族群
You can see that the sea peoples in our ancient area
你可见我们古代这一带的海洋民族
How divided is his ethnic group
他的族群的分歧有多大
How many different ethnic groups does he have
他有不同的族群有多少
So this is his age division
所以这个是他的年代分化
wide open
大开
Because the South Island has
因为讲南岛有
Now, for example, the academician Lirengui of our academy
現在比如說我們院理的理人鬼院士
They kept pushing and pushing until maybe six thousand years
他們一直推啊推到大概只能推到六千年
I saw it the other day
又第二天就見過這樣子
Did Lan Daoyu dare not say six thousand years ago?
那六千年之前是不是藍刀羽不敢說
he thinks not
他認為不是
Recently, I was at Connel University with Mr. Mei Zhulin
那最近我還跟梅主林先生在Connel大學
He recently corresponded with him
他最近跟他通信
on these issues
就談到這些問題
that is
就是說
should they linguists because they think
應該他們語言學家因為認為
Blue Sword Feather is
藍刀羽是
It is generally believed to be branched from Bluetooth
一般認為是從藍牙語分支出來的
but
但是
When their blue sword feather appeared
他們藍刀羽出現的時候
is already a full-fledged language
就已經是一個滿成熟的語言
So they all think that there should be a language
所以他們都認為是應該有一隻語言
It is gradually used from Bluetooth to Blue Daoyu
是從藍牙語變藍刀羽逐漸要用
have a status
有一個地位
maybe this is
也許這一點是
linguists to study
語言學家去研究
not us archaeologists
不是我們考古學家
so-called research questions
所謂的研究的問題
This is
這是
So the linguist actually asks
所以語言學家他其實的問題
differentiation problem
分化問題的
Probably know
大概知道
Because when Taiwan split up
因為台灣分化出去的時候
It's only about 4,000 to 5,000 years old
它的年代大概只四千到五千年
Li Dover
他們推測李多佛
not more than six thousand years
不會超過六千年
So this age of differentiation is like this
所以這分化年代是這樣的
So
那麼
South Island and Bamboo
到底南島與竹
actually when
其實是什麼時候來講
this
這個
This is their linguist
這個是他們語言學家
probably place to try again later
可能以後要再試的地方
That
那
generally believed
一般都認為
East Asia is the birthplace of Austronesian languages
東亞大陸是南島語言的起源地
that this
那這一點
because former linguists
是因為以前的語言學家
always
一直都
There are two important schools of thought
有兩個很重要的學派
one is considered to be
一個是認為是
Austronesian should
南島語應該
It should be China from Tibet to Sichuan to the Yangtze River Basin and then down
应该是中国从西藏进四川走长江流域再下来
Go down from the mouth of the Yangtze River Basin and go southeast
从长江流域口再下来沿着往东南走
A group of American scholars said that
有一批美国的学者说案
He thinks his language should be a trade language
他是认为他的语言应该是一个trade language
is a language of trade
是一个贸易的语言
Because everyone is talking about this
大家因为都在讲说一声这一声
These two academic
他应该在东南亚导誉发生的这两个学术
But if everyone has overturned the victim's academic theory by now
但是如果大概现在人都已经把受害人的学术已经推翻了
Probably everyone believes that Taiwan is the mother emperor
大概都相信是台湾是母帝
Because Taiwan is the most complicated place for Nan Daoyu
因为怎么台湾是难导宇最复杂的地方
Often the place where a language appears most complex
往往是一个语言出现最复杂的地方
it was one of the earliest locations
它是最早的一个地点
If Taiwan
假如台湾
but so early
但是那么早的话
So it's at the place of origin
那么它在起源地呀
where
哪里
won't be taiwan
不会是台湾
because all Taiwanese
因为所有台湾的
Aboriginal people now
现在的原住民
It's all coming in from the outside
都是外面进来的
mostly chinese
大部分是中国
Southeast coast
东南沿海
The Indochina Peninsula in the South China Sea brings
南中国海的中南半岛这一带来的
So this place of origin
所以这个起源地呀
can be sure
可以确定
already knocked over this
已经打翻了这个
The scholarship on the origin of the island domains of Southeast Asia
东南亚岛域起源的学术
This is
这是
So what about the domestic route?
那么至于国上的路线呢
this
这个
probably with
大概以
now for now
现在目前来讲
Both agree that it is from Taiwan
都同意是从台湾
into the Philippines
进菲律宾
To this South China Sea, this Indonesia
到这个南中海这个印尼
Island baby
岛娃
been going east
一直在往东
still going west
还有在往西
all the way to masgas
一直到马斯加斯
this area
这一带
then this
那么这个
The country's route
国上的路线啊
because
因为
if still
如果还是
Originally from mainland China
原来是从中国大陆
They are all from China
他们都是从中国的
It also needs to be rethought on the way of its diffusion
它的扩散路路上也要重新思考
So that's what I think the problem with the ocean's late-night habits
那么这个就是我认为海洋深夜的习性的问题
Many people have been thinking about saying
很多人都一直在考虑说
Do you think the universe will expand?
认为是难道宇宙会扩张的是
Because of the influence of the emergence of rice culture
因为受了稻米文化出现的影响
Then if Liangdao eight thousand years ago
那么如果八千年前的亮岛
this we saw it
这个我们看到了它
Apparently Bright Island is not a place that will be able to grow
显然亮岛不是一个会能够种植地
What is the plowing place for planting
种植有什么耕着的地方
So it might be looking for the universe
所以它可能在找的难道宇宙
Its late night is mainly hunting and gathering at sea
它的深夜是以海上的狩猎采集为主
while the rice is in
而稻米是在
I'm afraid it's a relatively late flower show.
是恐怕是比较晚的一个花展
So its fluid habit
所以它的生液的习性
Might also be a question to think about
可能也是一个要思考的问题
The eighth is the archaeological field method
第八个就是考古田野方法
This technical update when the human bone was excavated
这个人骨挖掘的时候的这个技术上的更新
I said that I am afraid that we will meet in the future
我就说恐怕以后大家遇到
Human bones must wear yellow clothes
人骨都要穿黄服衣的
I think that's probably an important point
我想这恐怕是很重要的一点
The fourth is
第四个就是
Previously because of this DNA study on the island of Goran
以前因为古兰岛屿的这个DNA研究
has been less successful
一直不太成功
what's the main thing
就主要怎么样
Because DNA extraction is too difficult
因为DNA萃取是太困难了
Let me know when we talk about Stone King
我们讲这个Stone King就告诉我
he told the truth
他说老实说
The extraction success rate of DNA from a thousand years ago is extremely low
一千年前的DNA的萃取成功率都极低
Not to mention our eight thousand years of success
更何况我们八千年成功
It has been successful for more than seven thousand years
七千多年也成功
but then again
但是话要讲回来
Stone King they became famous because
Stone King他们的成名是因为
Ye'an successfully obtained the DNA sequence of 40,000 years ago
也安得到四万年前的DNA水序成功
So its technology is always improving
所以它的技术是一直在进步的
So this is also possible in the future
所以这一点也是以后可能会
The research of our Liangdao people may stimulate these questions
我们亮岛人的研究恐怕会刺激到这些问题
let's see the next one
我们再看下一张
alright
好了
This is roughly what I figured out. Let’s talk about some not very important ones.
这个是我大致捏出来有一些不是很重要的我们讲
I also have a few books currently
我现在目前的书也有几本
I thought everyone would take turns
我本来是想大家轮流
Welcome to these three books
欢迎欢迎这三本书
My report looks like this for the first time
我的报告第一次是这样子
The second discovery of Liangdao people's DNA research another book
第二次发觉亮岛人DNA研究另外一本
In addition to this we have already discussed in some papers
除此之外我们已经在一些论文
some papers
一些论文
Also in the international
还有就是在国际性
It was in March last year
就是去年的3月就有
I already have one
我已经有一篇
I followed a family
我跟了个各家公子
Together we all wrote
合起来我们大家写的
This was published in the American Journal of Human Genetics in the United States
这个在美国的American Journal of Human Genetics发表
This is the world's top magazine published
这是世界第一顶尖的一个杂志发表
So our job is roughly
所以我们的工作大概
I have this next
我这还有接下来
we have an article coming out soon
我们马上有一篇快出来
In the following university I published a paper
在下面大学我发表了一篇论文
I published this one in this
我发表的这个有一篇在这个
This is in the EPA
这个在EPA
It was published by the Indo-Pacific Institute of Pedagogical Studies
就是印度太平洋这个考博学学会发表的
This paper is probably
这论文大概都
We're all in the process and we're all still publishing
我们都在陆续我们都还要出版
ok let's see the next one
好我们再看下一张
Our current research work
目前现在我们进行的研究工作
Research on the Periphery of Culture
对文化周边的研究
we must
我们就必须
because it's so bright
因为到底真亮倒
Cultures found in this location
这个位置发现的文化
According to his unearthed naughty, stony
依照他出土的淘氣、石氣
especially spine
尤其是骨氣
The county magistrate's favorite fisherman
縣長所最熱愛的漁差
What the hell is it around
我們到底它是周邊
What is the relationship with the surrounding culture?
跟周邊這個文化關係什麼樣
this is what we are going to study
這是我們要研究的
This behavior avoids learning
這個行態學避免學
this is to be studied
這個要研究的
paleoenvironmental science is very important
古環境學這很重要
paleoenvironmental studies when I was working in Liangdao
古環境學我曾經在量島工作的時候
i just noticed
我就注意到
I wonder why such a small island
我在想為什麼這麼小一個島
How could it be so popular after 8,000 years
怎麼會八千年久就這麼熱門
I pay attention to this ecological environment
我就很注意這個生態環境
because the horse owner
因為這個馬主人
This Daegu guy said
這個大丘的人說
must go there every year
每年一定要去那個地方
so he can see umbrella terroir
所以他可見雨傘風土
And this ecological environment
還有就是這個生態環境
8,000 years ago, the sea level
八千年前到底海平面
with this now
跟現在有這個
what is the change
變遷是怎麼樣
I once asked academician Liu Shaocheng of our research institute
我曾經請教我們研究院的劉少成院士
He said that eight thousand years is about 10 meters lower
他說八千年大概是降低10公尺的樣子
Well, Professor Chen Wanshan from the Geology Department of National Taiwan University
那麼台大的地質系的陳萬山教授
Say about 10 meters to 20 meters
說大概10公尺到20公尺之間
Academician Liu recently told me
最近劉院士又告訴我
He said that there is no 10 meters or about 3 or 4 meters.
他說沒有10公尺大概3、4公尺的樣子
So the doctrine keeps changing
所以這個學說一直在變
All in all he is lowered
總而言之他是降低的
I'm watching while lowering
降低的時候我在觀察
because i'm on a cliff
因為我在懸崖上
The mainland fishermen are fishing there
底下大陸漁民就在那摸魚
he's in the shallow water
他就在那淺水
I'm thinking if it's lower than 10 meters
我在想如果降低10公尺以內的話
Presumably his part is because the fishing ground is so
想必他那一塊因為漁場那麼
Every day when we dig there
他每天我們在那挖的時候
he harvests below
他在下面收穫
how is he
他怎麼樣
Come here every morning and don't go down
每天早上來這裡不予往下去
this ichthyosaur
這個魚龍
send down the fish bowl
把鱼丼送下去
Help Maru collect the ichthyosaur and go back
帮丸收鱼龙回去
Lay another ichthyosaur down
又铺一个鱼龙下去
Twice a day pays off
每天的两次都有收获
so
所以
How about it
怎么样
when it's bone
它骨的时候
If the sea level shift decreases
如果海平面移降低
its soup map
它的汤图
Bigger face
面移大
Tang Tu maybe that place Tang Lou Kuan
汤图也许那个地方汤楼宽
So its fish production is booming
所以它的鱼产就红火
More magnification
倍率多
So this is also our bone environment
所以这个也是我们骨环境
research is later
研究是以后
solving issues
处理问题
and the bone environment for
还有骨环境对于
Oxygen isotope analysis, etc.
汤氧同位素的分析等等
Animals, plants, grilled bones, etc.
动植物 烤骨绝等等
certainly
当然
Our work
我们的工作
after making it
做出来以后
So my most important thing is
所以我最要紧就是
i cook bone roast in taiwan
我在台湾做烤骨
Be sure to talk to the local people
一定要跟地方的人
I think
我觉得
Artifacts from this place
取自于这个地方的器物
should stay here
应该要保留在这个地方
so
所以
We measure the whole
我们整个量倒
For all the work of Matsu, I exchanged the specimens in the Matsu Folk Museum
馬祖所有的工作我都把標本換在馬祖民俗文物館
because it's local
因為它是當地啊
How can it have this social collection is what they want to collect
它要有怎麼有這個社會典藏是他們要典藏的
Social education is focused on their native land
社會教育是重點是在他們本土本地
This is my always Le Wei's policy
這是我一向的樂偉的方針
how do you see the next one
怎麼看下一張
Future goals Of course I want to deepen this research work
未來的目標當然我要深化這個研究工作
Algorithms of Institutional Capability
體制能力學運算學
Issues related to the stock environment
和股環境相關的問題
practical strategy
實應的策略
Research on the Peripheral Correlation of Material Culture
物資文化周邊關聯性的研究
In this way, lead to a comparative study on No. 1 and No. 2
這樣導人一號二號比較研究
this has to be done
這個都要做的
This is what we have done now
這個我們現在已經做出來的
I recently went to inspect the opening at this site
最近在這個現場去檢採開幕的
History Museum at History I Nanhai Road
在歷史我南海路的歷史博物館
is still on exhibition
現在還正在展覽
as free to see
作為有空可以去看
This guide and the archeology led by Mazu
這個量導跟馬祖列導的考古
Then we still have our model anyway
那我們還有我們這個反正的這個模型
we all made it
我們都做出來了
what we model
我們模型做的
The model of the face is being done now
臉部的模型現在正在做
not done yet
還沒做出來
And we except human bones
而我們除了人骨做好以後
What do we want the guard's face to look like?
我們還要護員臉什麼樣的樣子
So this is hope for our future work
所以這個是希望我們以後的工作
I'll take another look
我再看一下
This is the long picture I sent just now
這個就是我剛才送的現長的這麼一幅字
This word this is my mediocrity
這個字這個是我我的富庸風雅
this is not good
這個是不好
this is not a good poem
這不是好詩
I wrote the sequence like this
那這個序是我這麼寫
Just give it to the present boss
就是送給現長
This Shuhua family is my senior brother
這個舒華家是我的師兄弟
I have learned from Huang Beiyue's Shuhua family before
我以前跟黃北月的舒華家跟他學過
So I haven't written for decades
所以我這個幾十年不寫
I can't write my words
我的字不敢寫出來
dare not measure
不敢量
So I asked my brother to write this name
所以讓我的師兄弟寫這名福字
give to present
送給現長
thank you
謝謝各位
professor thank you
教授謝謝你
wonderful speech
好精彩的演講
first question
第一個問題
i want to ask
我想請問
that professor is
那個教授就是
professor
教授
you think you like
你覺得你很喜歡
Your favorite
你喜歡的
the professor is
教授就是
that about this
那個有關於這個
This number two massive girl
這個二號海量妹
and sister
和妹母孩
just say
就說
his Yanwu
他的那個延伍
was taken away
被取走了
Then I want to know the story too
那我也想知道這個故事
just take this
就取走這個
what is the motive for taking
取走的動機是什麼
then bring that
那再帶來就是那個
It was our Yangxian leader who found it.
是我們陽線長找回來的
Elder brother He Qin, our Yang line is long
阿哥 何秦 我們陽線長
tell us the secret
告訴我們這個秘密
how is it
是怎麼樣
How did you get him back?
去找他怎麼樣找回來的
get it back as a whole
找回來做整體
how difficult is it
是有多麼困難
The second is to say
第二個就是說
all of us
我們當中整個
that bug bone
那個蟲骨
worm bone of the whole wrist
整個腕子的蟲骨
The teeth you see are so neat
看到的那個牙齒好整齊
that is to say this
就是說這個
ancient man's teeth
上古時代的人的牙齒
Is it all like this? Is it so good?
都這個樣子嗎?這麼好嗎?
Is it because they belong to the exaltation of the ocean?
是不是因為他們是屬於海洋的崇起?
So capture more here
所以在此攝取得多
How can there be such a complete one?
才能有這麼完整的那一種?
thank you thank you
謝謝你 謝謝
Thank you Madam, what is your last name?
謝謝 請問女士貴姓
Shuang Mulin
姓雙慕林
Miss Ray
雷小姐
I'm going to apply for this now
這個我現在要申佈一下
Because of the above three problems
因為前面三個問題
I give everyone a souvenir of mine
每一個人我都送一個我的紀念品
This souvenir is an 8G USB
這紀念品是8個G的USB
and it has my name written
而且有寫我的名字
light up commemorative
在上面亮倒紀念
this souvenir
這紀念品
thank you professor
謝謝教授
I will answer first
我先回答
answer the question first
先回答問題
Let the magistrate answer his questions again
讓縣長再回答他的問題
The first question is
第一個問題就是
why can't i go into details
為什麼我不能夠細講的
It's because it's more tortuous in the middle
就是因為在中間比較曲折
and involved in the scene
而且牽涉到現場
The military is still scouting for undisclosed festivals
在军方还在侦察不公开的节观
so i can't tell anyone
所以我不能够讲什么人
probably a light
大概是一个一光
one light
一个一光
Only then did he realize the importance of this tooth
他才知道这个牙齿是重要性
Because in our conception before
因为以前我们的观念里头
I always thought that teeth are the best place to store DNA
一直以为牙齿保存DNA最好的地方
The study of teeth is the most important
牙齿的研究是最重要的
But in fact I just said
但事实上我刚才讲过
Sent three specimens to Germany
送了三件的标本去德国
teeth failed
牙齿没有做成功
Such a long leg bone did not succeed
这么长的腿骨没有做成功
Great work by the little ice cubes
小冰粒的大功了
It is the front of the big touch paper
就是大摸纸的最前面
Small straight bone succeeded
小直骨成功了
Most continued to succeed
最继续成功了
OK
OK
this is the first question
这个是第一个问题
The second question is
第二个问题就是
I'm probably the problem
我大概就是这个问题
right
对不对
I answer
我回答
That County Magistrate Yang, do you want to tell us about yourself?
那个杨县长你要不要讲你的
how did you find out
你这怎么发现的故事
Thank you, teacher
謝謝老師
press press talk
按 按講
no more no more
沒有了 沒有了
over there this
那邊這個
Well
呃
Let's talk about the embarrassing incident first
先講那個丟臉事件
then
當時
uh we judge
呃 我們判斷
judge say
判斷說
uh, someone who does this kind of thing
呃 會做這種事情的人
Not many people do this kind of thing
會做這種事情的人不多
uh everyone knows
呃 大家知道
if at home
如果是家裡
dropped things
掉的東西
hand stolen words
手人偷的話
There is a chance to defend the direction
方向保衛的機會有招
he is a direct hit
他是直接命中目標
If I get poached, I'll talk and laugh
如果被挖的話我也會談笑
He was poached at a very young age, expressing that he is familiar with this environment
很小就被挖走 表示說他對這個環境熟悉
probably answer like this later
大概這樣子回答 後來
This was found in a safe in Taichung
這個是在台中一個保險櫃裡面找到
because
因為
I
我
I like being a detective better than being a doctor
比當醫生更喜歡的是要當偵探 結果
Ha ha ha ha
哈哈哈哈
in addition
另外
Well
呃
We just said the head of the membership
我們剛才會員長說
For core core difference
對於蕊 蕊差
very interested why very interested because
很有興趣 為什麼很有興趣 因為
Teacher Chen dug the broken part for the first time
陳老師第一次挖到斷了那一截
later on
後面的時候
I've figured out what he's all about
我已經想到他整個是什麼樣子
The result was in when digging in the second round
結果進了 在第二局挖的時候
dig out the whole
把整個完整的挖出來
Well
呃
I have a
我有一個
The friend who wrote the fishing exhibition in Taiwan is called Li Jialiang
台灣寫釣魚文展的朋友 叫李嘉亮
Fishing known as Taiwan
號稱台灣的釣魚
The world has written many articles
世界 寫了很多文章
he told me
他告訴我說
more than ten thousand years ago
一萬多年前
There are people in Taiwan who are willing to make up for the surplus
台灣就有人願餘差來補餘
so this
所以這個
suddenly we see
忽然間我們看到
when the gap was broken
那個斷的餘差的時候
imagine what it should be like
想到應該是什麼樣子
When we look at that full residual
當我們看到那個完整的餘差的時候
Let's see him every step of the way
我們去看他每一個步驟
every place
每一個地方
his function
他的功能
What is his anatomical function
把他解剖功能是什麼
he has his function
他都有他的功能
when i saw
當時看到的時候
Is it Yucha or the original Yugou?
到底是餘差還是原始的餘勾
later thought
後來想
he should be Yuchai
他應該是餘差
because the front is pointed
因為前面是尖的
For the convenience of founding
為了方便創始
he has hook
他有盜勾
is to prevent drag peach
是防止拖桃
In addition
另外後面
There is a hook for the rope
有一個把繩子的勾槽
specially engraved
特地刻出來的
means to say
就是表示說
At that time there must be a rope to hold
那個時候一定有繩子把著
But now after the fish cavity is played
但是現在魚腔打了以後
let it run over the line pull
讓它跑越線拉
Ears running from Bright Island One at the same time
同時從亮島一號跑的耳朵
Has the inherent disease of divers
具有潛水夫固有的病
We boldly recommend that people from Liangdao are second only to diving.
我們大膽的推就是亮島人是潛水居次於
But the main interest is those things
但是最主要有興趣的是那些東西
The environment in which we recruit
在我們中招的環境
In the environment where we grew up, I feel that these are very familiar
在我們小小生長的環境裡面覺得這些都很熟悉
We just took what we found
我們只是把發現的這些東西
Imagine and fight with the classmates at that time
跟那個時候的同學去想像去鬥在一起
found that archeology and anthropology are both interesting
發現說考古學跟人類學都很有趣
thank you all
謝謝大家
I just changed my answer to your question.
我結許剛才換了回答你這問題
about teeth
就關於牙齒
This tooth is 32 grams of teeth all in
這牙齒它是32克牙齒全部都在
probably
大概就是
this is our luck
這個是我們很幸運的
so unnecessary
所以不必要
who else
還有哪一位
second place
第二位啊
OK, let's take a look first.
好你先來看看
let me ask this
我請問一下這個
1600's economy team
1600的經濟隊
Looks like it grew from a heterosexual body
看起來是從異性體長到的
right
對
not from that
並不是從那個
The human body is grown from high school
人生體就是從高中長到的
These two are different ones
這兩個是不同的那個
series people
系列人
heterogeneous
異類
The nucleus is not from the nucleus
細胞核不是從細胞核
from the cytoplasm
是從細胞質能跟照樣
While looking for this
那這個找的同時
it should have several pairs
它應該有好幾對的
what we call factor
我們所謂的因子
So it should if found
所以應該它如果找得到
The economic team in 1900 was quite long
1900的經濟隊那很蠻長的
According to this should also find
照這個應該也會找到
BMA of other parts
其他的部分的BMA
If there is more BMA
那如果BMA多一點的話
Will this detection classification
這個檢測分類是不是會
be more precise
更精細一點
The other is to say
那另外一個就是說
this number 2
這個2號
It's hundreds of years late
是晚了幾百年了
But now it's a different job
但是現在是不同的重勤
Could it be that they prove each other
會不會是他們是互相證明的
Sometimes the early days come and conquer this early stage
有的時候那天初期來了把這點初期征服掉
Or what, so if you cancel the tail, I will just cancel you
還是怎麼樣所以消尾掉我把你就是消尾掉
That is the key to whether you will have the possibility this time
那就是會不會你這次會不會有可能性關鍵
That
那
The first question I want to answer is about
我要回答第一個問題就是關於
right
對
In fact, the so-called DNA
其實所謂的DNA
That is its whole and complete yin and shoulder skin.
那個就是它整個完整的陰化又肩膚反又是
There is a muscle reducing pair
有個減肌對
So the main thing is that it needs a lot of stink, that is, it stinks.
所以主要這個這個是要很多臭就是臭起來
A card to it don't let it have missing
一隻牌對它不要讓它有缺失
So what I just said is
所以我剛才講的是
what i just said is
我剛才講的就是
because it was made because its experimental results become
因為它做出來是因為它的實驗結果就變成
There are 16569 clip pairs that can be very complete
可以很完整的16569剪輯對都有
so it can make its sequence out when
所以它才能做出它的序列排出來時
1 Between 10,000 and 10,000 A
1 1萬到1萬A之間
it's me because i didn't do it myself
是我因為我不是我自己做
I don't know very well
我不是很清楚
But I understand it this Metrocontrast is what it is
但是我了解它這個Metrocontrast就是這樣的
But about Why Cramor Song
但關於Why Cramor Song
Now in fact we haven't published
現在事實上我們還沒有公布
In fact, the one made is between O1 and O1A
事實上一做出來的是O1到O1A之間
Why can't this be published now?
這個現在目前為什麼不能公布
Because they do this DNA research business
因為他們做這個DNA研究這一行
It cannot be published arbitrarily
它不能夠任意的公布出去
announced one day
有一天公布出去
its thesis
它的論文
it's going to be discounted
它的就要打折扣
People think you've published
人家認為你已經公布了
so it's like this
所以是這樣子
So I'm just getting started
所以我目前只是初步了解
Certain papers are currently being written
一定論文現在已經正在寫之中
to be lighter
要更特輕
The second question is
第二个问题是
These two sentences are because you want
这两句就是因为你想
What I just said was
本来我刚刚讲的就是
ocean of this generation
这一代的海洋
It's basically multi-ethnic groups wandering and drifting
根本就是多族群在流荡在漂流
so today i come tomorrow
所以今天我来明天
Longing for them to be hundreds of years apart
渴望他们隔好几百年
so what is their relationship in the middle
所以在中间他们是什么关系
we really don't know
我们实在是不知道
But the odds are too high
但是可能性太大了
because think about it
因为想想看
In ancient times, if these ethnic groups drifted on the sea
古代如果在海上漂流的这些族群
Because why can we differentiate
因为我们能为什么会分化出来
different ethnic groups
不同的好像能族群
Mainly because we can have mutation
主要是因为我们能会有mutation
there will be this change
会有这个变
mutation
突变
The result of the mutation will be
突变的结果就会产生
Almost said a mutation before
以前差不多说一个突变
It takes about 8,000 years for the human master to mutate
人主的突变大概要8000年
So I believe that those who study them think that there may be a picture in about 5000-3000 years
所以我相信他们这些研究的人认为大概可以说到5000-3000年就可能有个图片
There may be a group of pictures
能就可能有一群的图片
So we don't know yet
所以这一点我们现在还不能知道
Apparently it's because it's two different matrilines
显然它因为它是两个不同的母系
And we know that its fine drop is from the generation from the war to the Indochina Peninsula
而且我们知道它的细落一个是从战免一直到中南半岛这一代
One is our southeast coast of China
一个是我们中国东南沿海
So its origin is these two different origins
所以它的出处是这两不同的出处
Apparently it's done differently
显然又是做出来不一样
But I forgot to mention that Germans are beautiful
但我刚才忘了提到德国人很成长美
Very grown up our yellow clothes
很成长我们的穿黄户衣
He said it was a pioneering work
他说这是一个创举
He said the DNA I made turned out to be zero pollution
他说我做出来的DNA结果是零污染
no pollution at all
一点污染都没有
so it's very clear
所以这是非常清晰的
Every part of the stories I just told is important.
我刚才讲的这些故事每一个环节都很重要
every link is important
任何一个环节都很重要
If a link is missing, I am afraid
假如缺一个环节恐怕
Of course we are responsible for this.
我们这个当然我们成国会大责
This is what I want to answer
这个这是我要回答
I want to give this friend
我要送给这位朋友
once or twice
一二回
I would like to ask the professor
我会想请问一下教授
What I just said is more related to the results of the exam
就是刚刚讲的比较多的事关与考过的结果
I was wondering if you could tell us more about
我想说你可不可以再跟我们多介绍一下
About people around the island
关于环岛人
They were born anthropologically
他们生开在人类学上
what kind of state is it
是一个什么样的状态
Especially at the place where the white tent was just now
尤其刚在那白帐的地方
all in water
都在水难上
In that state, many ancient people were academic officials
那种状态很多古代人是学官
seniors accounted for high
学长占颁高
Then life learns the zone of life
那么生活就学生活的地带
Because the islander has less than one
因为那个岛人面致不到一个
so how could they be in the same voice
所以他們可能是怎麼樣的同聲
and some headlines
還有一些頭片
how should their lives be
他們生活性應該怎麼樣
To be introduced from the University section
要從大學的部分介紹
Thanks
謝謝
Actually the story is too long
其實這個故事太長
I'm afraid I'm going to make a long story short
恐怕我要長話短說
This is our archeology guy
這是我們考古學的人
Because especially prehistoric archeology
因為尤其是史前考古
Because he has no written record
因為他沒有文字的記載
so all these jobs
所以所有的這些工作
material culture
都要依靠物質文化
come tell us some stories
來告訴我們一些故事
we're going to create it
我們要把它創起來
These are prehistoric artifacts
這是史前的這些器物
We are left with these words
我們留給我們的是這幾句
The second is his ecological environment
第二個就是他的生態環境
leave it to us
留給我們
this question is important
這個問題很重要
My guess on this ecological environment
這生態環境我的推測
Our place just now
剛才我們那一塊地方
It turns out that there is nothing wrong with him being a cliff. It should be an evil soul, but this cross section is only possible because the road opened.
原来他是一个悬崖是没有错的,原来应该是一个邪魄,但是因为马路一开所以才有这个断面。
So it turned out that when they came down from the northeast, the place of the evil soul could probably block some wind. This is why they should only live in the inner zone at the earliest.
所以原来他们东北下来的时候,那个邪魄那个地方大概可以挡一些风,这是一点他们最早应该只居住在内带。
But their place of residence, and we found that the second place is a little bit past that place, and that place is flatter, maybe that place is where they live and throw garbage here,
但是他们的居住地,还有我们发现第二地点过去一点那个地方更平,也许那一块地方是他们居住地把垃圾丢在这个地方,
It can also be pushed to the cold field with great difficulty, maybe it is like this, but then again, the phenomenon of the fire pit under the second sentence is obviously a place where people live, and people live there and live here.
也可以好容易推到寒野去,也许是这样的,但是话讲回来,第二句底下有火塘的现象显然是人居住的地方,人在那生活在这里居住居住。
So we're still working on that.
所以这一点我们还在研究之中。
Of course, the relationship is also very close, a great relationship. The inner land is obviously not very easy to live in, so I am talking about, in our prison ecology, a very important point for people living in prisons is that the big island is often attached to the mainland, and the small island is attached to the big island.
当然关系也很密切,很大的关系。内块地显然不是很容易居住,所以我在讲,我们导狱生态里面,导狱生活的人非常重要的一点就是,大岛往往要依附大陆,小岛依附大岛。
An island domain is a complete ecological environment, but the material conditions inside are limited. Many things have to be exchanged with each other.
一个岛域是一个完整的生态环境,但是里面的物质条件是有限的。很多东西都要靠彼此交换。
For example, if the island does not have it, there is no way to eat it, and you will not be able to step on the fruit. If you eat protein and fish protein all day long, you will not live long, and you will not live long. It must be starchy, so it must be exchanged.
比如那个岛,它如果没有,没办法龙羹也踩不到果实,你一天到晚吃蛋白质,鱼类蛋白质,活不了多久,活不了多长,它一定要淀粉质,所以一定要交换。
So that island, the Matsu Islands, can be seen from the other side, and almost every island can see the other side.
所以那个岛,马祖列岛,看到对岸都看得见的,每个岛差不多都可以看到对岸。
This is because he has to cling to his counterpart
這個就是因為他要依附著對樣
So he's obviously going to catch Yu and come here and live for a while
所以他顯然是要抓於來這裡活一陣子過一陣子
or seasonal
或者是季節性的
not a permanent resident
不是永久的居民
Definitely Not
一定不是
can you answer this question
能不能回答這個問題
for this I
這個我
this is the last side
這個是最後一面
Thanks
謝謝
Speaking
請講
Hello Professor Chen
陳教授你好
I think I have a question and I want to ask you
我想我有問題想請問您就是
Apart from actually seeing shellfish
除了實際看到貝種
Know that there are cultural sites other than
知道這裡有文化遺址之外
Because other clues can be speculated that
因為其他的線索可以去推測說
There will be cultural relics here
這邊會有文化遺址
in this way
這樣子
Usually we archaeologists
通常我們做考古的人
Let's go
我們去
we are going to the fields
我們要到田野去
when going to investigate
去調查的時候
obviously
顯然
not easy to see first not easy to see
不容易看到最先不容易看到
The first and most important thing to judge is the ecological environment
最先判斷最要緊的就是生態環境
Water is the most important
水源最要緊
if there is no water
假如沒有水
people
人啊
he can't live there
他根本在那地方生活不了
So the water source is the most important
所以水源最要緊
So let's say we measure down this place
所以我們譬如說量倒這個地方
look at him
你看他的樣子
How could he have no river
他怎麼會又沒有河
and no
又沒有
But what's interesting is
但是很有意思的就是
Measure the lower layer
量倒的下面一層
There are many caves entering the bay
進海灣的有很多山洞
there is spring water on it
上面有泉水
early days
早期的時候
200 troops are stationed there
駐軍200人在那裏
no supplies
沒有補給
no water supply
沒有水的補給
how do they live
他們怎麼活
They are washbasins
他們就是臉盆去
Use the spring water at the bottom of the cliff to line the water
在懸崖底下的泉水去襯水來用
includes a basin of water
包括一盆水
including face wash
包括洗臉洗
do many things
做很多事情
to the last
到最後還要交為
When we go to investigate, the most important thing is to first check whether the environment is inhabited and where is the water source? Probably like this
我們去調查,最要緊的就是第一個看看那個環境是不是住人,水源在哪裡?大概是這樣
Islands like this, of course, are places close to the sea, which is relatively safe, like being on a cliff, I can’t figure out why I’m going back there, this is also art, so let’s talk about it
像這種島嶼,當然是靠近海汪的地方,是比較可,像在懸崖,我在想不出為什麼回在那裡,這個也是藝術,話講回來
If it wasn't so high, if it wasn't for its formation, which is sandy red soil, this human bone would not have been preserved for so long
假如不是那麼高,假如不是它的地層,是沙子的紅土,這個人骨一定是不會保存這麼久
Because usually our archeology will find human bones, which are usually inside the shellfish, and the shellfish is a protective layer, because the shells on it are so well covered
因為上面通常我們的考古會發現人骨,是通常是在貝種裡面,貝種是一個保護層,因為它上面蓋的貝蓋得那麼好
He said coldly that Le Zhan had nothing to do with it.
他冷說樂戰關係不了的
he doesn't get through
他不容易透過
The laterite water of the sand has flowed away
沙子的紅土水都流掉了
so he is dry
所以他很乾燥
In that life his place is dry
在那生活上他這個地點很乾燥
So I guess these are the conditions
所以我想這些都是條件
Of course I have a good chance
當然我這人機遇很好
After a lifetime of archaeology, I dug up these two sentences
搞了一輩子考古就這兩句挖到
Everything else is digging a lot of light
其他全部是把光挖了一大堆
No one makes up
沒有人補
thanks sorry i'm out of ideas
謝謝對不起我的想法沒有了
Feel sorry
抱歉
Thanks
謝謝
Is there any more?
還有嗎
I am a southern nation
我這個南方這個民族
Are you called a Pulician?
是不是叫做普利利西亞人
Because when I arrived in Ryukyu
因為我到琉球的時候
he kept that time
他留住那時候
But it's like this from the mainland
但是從大陸過來就這樣講
He said no, we are a southern democracy, so we don’t care about it.
他說不是 我們是南國民主是不理會想
just to leave a little place
就是要留下一個小小的地方
that language has six or five
那個語言有六五
no
不是
Another one is Beijing Yuanren and this
還有一個是北京原人和這個
But naturally they say the term "big Buddha"
但自然的話他們講這個大佛名詞
and this
還有這個
These
這些
this
這個
because we are old
因為我們年紀大
still not sure
還搞不清楚
Thanks
謝謝
The Lycians are in the middle of the Pacific Ocean
在利西亞人是在太平洋中間
that is now next
那個現在在下位
Since the South Island universe is a kind of country since Beijing
在南岛宇宙以来是在北京以来的一种国家
In the South Island Universe we are talking about, there used to be a man named Marel Polaris
我们讲的南岛宇宙以前有的人叫马来尔·波莱利斯
he is not australian
他不是澳洲人
The Austronesian universe we are talking about
我们讲的南岛宇宙
napoles is to the east
那波莱利斯是在东边
a district in the middle of the pacific east of vip doppin
在贵多宾以东那边的太平洋中间的一个区
About Peking Man because he is 500,000 to 600,000 years old
关于北京人因为他有五六十万年
From now on, if he is not now, he cannot be compared with our current race.
距离现在他不是现在跟我们现在的人种是不能相提并论的
because he is a branch of anthropology
因为他是人类学的分支流
He is called Homo erectus pecinesis
他是叫做Homo erectus pecinesis
Homo erectus Beijing species
就是直立原人北京种
He is hundreds of thousands of years old
他好几十万年
Many of us think that the Chinese are Beijing
我们很多人就认为中国人是北京
The main line is Pekingese
主线是北京人
wrong
不对的
out of africa theory
出非洲的理论
There are two different things with Beijingers
跟北京人是两码之事
Because in those early days, those people felt that
因为那时候早期的时候那些人都觉得
We are now probably after we came out of Africa
我们现在大概是从非洲出来以后
It probably came out around 60,000 years ago
大概出来的时候差不多六万年左右
Only came out between 50,000 and 60,000 years
五六万年之间才出来
Distributed all over the world
分布到现在全世界各地
This is probably like this
这个大概是这样子
Thanks
谢谢
Just now you asked me that the whole teacher was slightly ahead of schedule
刚才你问了我整个老师有稍微的提前
I'm a researcher
我是研究图然
To suddenly say that the US job is written similar to the investment
要突然说美国工作写的跟投资的类似
The question I just asked is
刚才我来问的问题就是说
The archaeologist you found has been back and forth
你发现的考古人一直在背上下
Then you were sometimes protected on your back just now
那你刚才有时候是背上保护的地方
I'm thinking maybe it's also because of the carbon build-up
我在想说可能也是因为碳增盖
But for soils that have a handover effect
但是对于有土壤会形成交接作用
It is not easy to distinguish between various protections
对各种保护对它不容易分大
I feel at ease when I was a flower girl like this when I was a child
那小時候這樣的花納,那我就安心
The second point is that you are here
第二點就是說你在這邊
Dig up to 8000 years ago
挖到8000年前的量導
7000 years of volume guide
7000年的量導內
Is it possible to continue digging at this amount?
是不是在這個量還可以繼續再挖下去
1,000 years, 4,000 years, and 3,000 years can be found
可以發現1000年的、4000年的三千年的
and that's it
這樣就就完成
thank you thank you
謝謝,謝謝你
Number one, you're low on power
第一點,你低一點執政
coaching, coaching very happy
執教,執教非常高興
Because in fact, it is probably carbonic acid
因為其實被,大概就是碳酸概類
is that it was planted in this layer
就是它被種這層
It itself has protection against the energy body
它本身有對能體是有保護
For example, in our archeology in Taiwan
譬如說我們台灣的考古學裡面
The original businessman is planted to produce human bones
原商被種就出人骨
Because how it was planted inside
因為怎麼它是被種裡面
So it can only come out after being planted
所以被種裡面才能出
The protection I just mentioned is useful
我剛才講的這個保護成所用
the second you talk about this
第二個你談到這個
i'm so sorry
就是我非常抱歉
Can you still dig in eight days?
八天你還能不能挖
I have to answer this
我這個要回答
Because of that whole chair you just watched Zai Cangchang's
因為那個整個椅子你剛剛看了宰宰殘長的
Of course you can dig
那當然還可以挖
But those of us who do archaeology often have a principle
但是我們做考古的人往往我們有一個原則
The smaller the area to dig
就是挖的面積要越小
The more information obtained, the more
取得的這個資料越豐富越多
we're going to stop
我們就要停掉了
because if you dig again
因為你如果再挖的話
It's probably amazing. I need to add a little more to your business.
大概了不起跟你這個什麼企務多加一點
But we have to think about the descendants of our archaeologists
但是我們要為我們考古學的人的後代要著想
Because all subjects are closer to Nikkei
因為所有的學科都是日經越近的
His current technology may be better than ours in the future
他現在我們的技術說不定以後會比我們更好
we gotta save some sanity for them
我們要為他們留一些理智
this is the point
這個才是重點
Thanks
謝謝
Mr. Liu
劉先生
teacher sorry
老師抱歉
bother your time
打擾你的時間
I have a question
我有一個問題
I study
我研究
previous climate
之前的氣候
besides
還有
China's climate change in the past 2000 years
中國一張2000年來的氣候變化
I think
我想
Southeast coast
東南沿海
Talk to Teacher Chen
跟陳老師講
Measure the elderly
量老人
About 7 or 8 years old
年代差不多7、8歲
7, 8, 7 years now
現在7、8、7年間
they were
當時他們
our ancestors
我們的祖先
very early in the southeast
很早在東南
Southeast China and South China
中國大陸東南國還有華南
there were activities at that time
那時候有活動
Measure the elderly
量老人
At the time
當時的
performance of life and climate
生活的表現還有氣候
Is it with South China
是不是跟華南
The generation on the southeast coast
東南沿海那一代的
Thanks
謝謝
actually related
其實是相關的
I believe it should not be a small area problem
我相信是應該不是小區域的問題
For example, let me make a metaphor
譬如我打個比喻
Like we just talked about sea level
比如我們剛剛談到海平面的問題
Sea level rise is after the ice age
海平面上升是冰期以後
During the ice age, its sea level was about 120 meters away from the present
冰期的時候它的海平面距離現在大概120公尺左右
lower so low
降低那麼低
So it's hard for us to find it now
所以再找的我們現在很難發現到
Because it must be close to the sea and must be under the sea.
因為它一定是靠海的一定都在海底底下的
Then the rise is from slowly rising slowly to
那麼上升由慢慢慢慢上升到
It was only about 6,000 years ago that it was relatively stable
距今現在差不多6千年左右才比較穩定
During the 8,000 years, of course, there was a little gap between about 1 or 2 meters.
那8千年它中間當然有一點起伍大概在1兩公尺這樣子
So presumably this climate change is global
所以大概這個氣候的變遷是全球性的
Of course, locality doesn't matter that much.
當然局部性的影響不是那麼大
I'm going to say this
我要這麼講
Thanks
謝謝
I really want to ask about the Japanese scriptures
好想請教一下日本的神文
Their savanna pottery also developed 10,000 years ago
他們的聲聞陶也是發展在一萬年前
It is also believed that they are talking to fish
也是被認為說他們是跟魚
It's like saying it belongs to Zhuang
等於是說屬於莊
Sorry, I'm not sure how to define it
不好意思我不太確定應該怎麼定義的意思
I think this thing is very similar to the marine industry with a small number of people.
我覺得這個東西就很跟量少人的海洋生業
maybe there is something related
可能是不是也有一些相關
Don't want professors to behave in this respect
不想要教授對這方面表現
thank him for this
謝謝他這個對
The test of Japanese programs is divine writing
日本節目的考求就是神文
Divine language and other culture
神文它文化
They can find around 12,000 years
他們可以找到一萬兩千年左右
It also appeared in the later period of the army
也是兵後期出現的
Their scriptures are thicker and thicker
他們的神文比較粗很粗
very crude scriptures
很粗套的神文
probably like this
大概這樣子
Basically because Japan basically it's islands
基本上因為日本基本上它是島嶼
island country
島嶼國家
So it's still a form or an island life form
所以它還是形態還是島嶼的生活形態
Of course Japan has many
當然日本有很多
So now there is a country in the world that studies islands called the Small Island Association
所以現在世界研究島嶼的國家有一個叫Small Island Association
is the island
就是小島
It only studies populations that cannot exceed 100,000
它只研究人口不能夠超過十萬人
This area cannot exceed
這個面積不能超過
I can't remember, and it's very clear that tens of square kilometers are like this
我記不來也很清楚幾十平方公里這樣子
Zhou Research Isle
周研究小島
Because the distance between the big island and the small island is actually quite big.
因為大島小島其實距離還蠻大的
It's quite a big gap
它的差距還蠻大的
But basically relying on the sea is related to the sea
但是基本上靠海邊才是跟海有關係
Oshima still has some
大島的話還是有一些
For example, we have so many in Taiwan
比如我們台灣那麼多
Later, the aborigines all ran away and all lived on the mountain.
後來的原住民都跑了都在山上
But was it chased?
但是是不是被趕上去的
no
不是
It turned out to be suitable for mountains and hills
原來就是適合於山地丘陵
they go to the mountains and hills
他們去找山地丘陵
it won't be on the plains
它不會在平原上
This is another one
這個是另外一道
We spent too long and I will not talk more
我們花太長我不變的多講
Thanks
謝謝
This our vice president is taking the exam
這個我們副院長在考試
this test me
這考我
This text teacher said
這個文老師講
All chairs are important to us
所有的椅子在我們心目中都重要
Of course there are chairs
當然椅子有分
by its nature
分它的性質 年代
its size its scale its integrity
分它大小 它的規模 它的完整性
This hierarchy is a false name
這個有層次是虛名
But the importance is actually important
但是重要性其實都是重要
But some so-called unimportant
但有的所謂不重要就是
it if many of the same chairs
它如果同樣的椅子很多的話
you don't write it's importance
你就不寫得它的重要
it's important to separate
它重要要分開了
its layers are going to separate
它的層次要分開了
But like Liangdao this is
但是像亮島這樣子這是
Taichu
太中間
because he is too little
因為他太少了
Thanks
謝謝
Time is up
時間到了
we are very happy today
我們今天很高興
Professor Chen gave a wonderful speech
陳教授有一個精采的演講
Professor Chen is 80 years old
陳教授已經80歲了
looks young
看起來很年輕
He is a self-taught
他是一位自學成功
Family Scholars
成家的學者
special come
特別的來得
We applaud him again
我們再次掌聲向他自行
Thanks
謝謝